He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons, and saints.
and scenes.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism
to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young
host this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation.
The union of the scene and unseen as made
by God and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, giants killers and giants killer,
but it's easy for me to say.
Giants killers, dragon slayers, it's a giants killers.
I think that becomes a football thing then.
You are listening to Lord of Spirits podcast.
My co-host Father Stephen D'Young is with me
from Lafayette, Louisiana,
and I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick
in Emmaus, Pennsylvania.
We are recording live, but we're actually
not going to be taking phone calls tonight.
That said, if you leave a question on our Facebook or ancient faith YouTube streams and we
spot it, there is a chance that we could take it and respond.
So tonight, we're talking about textual authority.
I know that sounds like a hoot, but stick with me here.
As Christians, whether it's the Bible, the apocrypha, the writings of the church fathers, texts
related to the ecumenical councils or the divine services.
We have a lot of texts.
So how are we supposed to understand these various texts?
In what sense are they authoritative?
That's what we're talking about tonight.
Now as we are want to do,
we're going to begin looking at this question
in the ancient world, thousands of years ago,
beginning even before the writings
that make up the holy scriptures.
So what's up first tonight, Father Stephen?
Are we gonna look at that Sumerian clay tablet
where someone complains about how kids don't obey
their parents anymore?
things just aren't what they used to be.
No. Oh. Oh well. Not quite that far back. So I have to comment. People may hear the
difference, but I have this new technology setup thing happening now. Yeah, you sound
so much better. And like with the headphones and the way my mic is set up on my desk, I
sort of feel like I'm guest hosting the delicious dish. But I'm not.
So I will not even attempt NPR voice any from you.
But so yeah, we're not starting quite that far back with the first piece of writing ever
because as far as we can tell that piece of writing was just a grumpy old man like me
and is not actually authoritative in any way for anyone.
I do love that that is the earliest known piece of writing is someone complaining how things
are going downhill and just not what they used to be.
Now they have-
gone back up really. But that's not true. Sumerian Renaissance was definitely a slight
uptick. But yeah, so we're talking about texts that play a particular kind of role in a community
tonight. Right. So complete notes like that or hate mail or
grocery lists, trade receipts. We're going to leave those aside and talk about first things
that aren't the Bible, that even proceed anything in the Bible, but that had a function in
their respective communities in the ancient Near East that were something like the function
that the Bible would come to have.
Yeah.
And so specifically, we're talking about these texts that form out of a preceding oral recitation
or oral tradition, right, and oral use of storytelling or narrative or ritual performance
that then eventually gets written down.
I'm sure that guy complained about kids these days all the time before it was written down,
But that's still not quite...
not quite what we were talking about.
So the, these tax, as I mentioned,
whether it's a narrative story,
whether it's a story that we would now call myth or mythology,
whether it's direct sort of ritual instructions.
These aren't things that are invented when somebody comes and sits down to write them down.
Right?
Like you can't just think.
up, well I mean Elron Hubbard did, but most people can't just think up a bunch of rituals
so they'd get people to go along with them.
Usually these are things that form semi-organically.
We talked about that back when we talked about sacrifices and encounters with spiritual
beings.
But so a couple of early examples that are kind of helpful in terms of what we're talking
about.
at least people who listen to this show.
have probably heard of the Anuma Ailesh, which is the sort of Babylonian creation account.
And we've talked before the show about the difference between myth and mythology.
Yeah, right.
That a myth is a story that has this sort of ritual component that sort of keeps that story alive
and makes it real in the experience of people.
When all of that drops out, it becomes mythology.
Right, add so most...
folks, I'd wager who have read the Anuma Ailesh have approached it as mythology.
Yes, just a story that doesn't actually play a part in their life in any way, except maybe as a
piece of entertainment. Right, or, or, you know, from a very sort of Protestant perspective,
we say, oh, this is what the ancient Babylonians believed about how it was created. Right, right.
So it's about thoughts or beliefs, right?
And this isn't just picking on our...
innocent friends, right? Like everyone does this. We all tend to think of other religions
in terms of our own religion, right? Because our own religion is the religious experience
that we have. So it was sort of natural for Protestant scholars when they started studying
ancient religion to look at it in terms of beliefs, right? And what people held
to. And so, and then going forward as there were sort of wars that we talked about, you
and how and how not to read the Bible episode.
They're sort of...
wars over how to read the creation account in Genesis, right? Then when people turn to
the Babylonian creation account, they tended to read it the same way, right? So either they
said, well, this is just sort of poetic, right? Interesting stuff. Or they said, no, this
is exactly how they believed it happened, right? But the Anuma Ailesh actually in Babylon was
actually reenact it.
every year. Yeah right. There was a there were a series of
processions to a sacred cigarette and the processions were
considered to be processions of the gods. So the the idol that
was the body of Marduk was picked up and carried down there.
And the the idols of the other gods from the other cities were
carried there in procession. And then there was this reenactment
with.
the king embodying Marta in the story.
Yeah, and it wasn't understood just as a kind of play, right?
Like, look, we're putting on a story, but this thing
is happening again and we're part of it.
Right.
We're participating in it.
And the reason it kept being done is, of course,
this is how the world was created.
And as we've pointed out for ancient people,
This isn't about being versus nothingness.
Because especially when you look at the enuma aile, there's nothing created out of nothing.
Everything's created out of something else.
But it's things being put in order.
And so this gets repeated and participated in as a way of maintaining that order.
And this is a pretty constant factor in all kinds of pagan religions.
You look at Mesoamerican human sacrifices that was to maintain the ordering of the world and keep it from ending.
Yeah huh
If you don't do this ritual, then really bad bad things will happen.
Yeah.
And so this was the same kind of thing.
This was maintenance, right, of the order, by reenacting.
It was actually doing something.
But of course, that annual festival, all of those ritual elements are now gone.
And so now it just sort of gets read as mythology.
Another example, and this one's a pretty obvious example, right.
This is an a narrative text per se, though there are narrative elements of it.
is the Egyptian book of the dead.
Which is basically a manual for doing funerals
in the Egyptian religious tradition.
Right, so it's all the funerary and burial rights.
And so that includes some sort of narrative elements
about Osiris and Enubis and the gods.
But those narrative elements are then actually sort of
played out in the rituals.
Yeah, that you by doing the ritual you are particular.
participating in Osiris' story of him dying and that sort of thing.
Right. So what's happening when these things are written down? Right? So these stories are still being told
orally. They're being passed on orally and they're being enacted in this ritual. What happens when they
finally get written down? Right? Is that once they're written down, that becomes the normative form. Right?
Now...
this is the written form. We talked before about how expensive and difficult writing something
down was, so it is written as this big statement, right? It's like a literary monument.
And you still find this in oral cultures to this day. In oral cultures, you can have two people,
two storytellers from that culture tell the same story, and their tellings of it can be radically
different right one could be an hour long and one could be 20 minutes long and
Yet if you ask one of the storytellers who listened to the other,
did they tell it correctly?
They say, yes.
It was totally different than their own telling.
But in those same cultures, once a version of that story
gets written down, then correct becomes
conforming to the written text.
Yeah.
And then any telling that doesn't conform to that,
or any ritual enactment that doesn't follow the text
once it's written down.
Right is now wrong is now correct right yeah look at do it by the book
essentially right and so
This is this is a way of
Establishing something like that permanently of reducing variation right and of locking in a
true version and and this is why this is a part of
We've talked about before several times other show how a number of
the narratives and non-narratives, poetry and the Psalms, elements in the Old Testament,
especially, will take elements of ancient Near Eastern religion and other cultures and
invert them or change them or correct them.
Here's the true version of what happened with Bales insurrection against the most high.
And the Old Testament doing that is not like
weird thing, right? The fact that it's written down already carries with it culturally
this idea of this is now going to be the correct version. Yeah and I think that's a really important
point about the way actually the whole Bible in a lot of ways functions it's not it's not that
it was written down to create a whole system of religious belief and structures and rituals
and so forth.
but rather that it came about within an existing social reality, and it doesn't come out of nowhere.
It's not a founding document, it's not a Constitution.
Although, if you think about the US Constitution, it is very self-consciously a response to other kinds of government.
So it's a response.
The scripture, one of the ways to look at it is that it's a response to other things that are already...
happening on the ground and it's an attempt to correct that to fix it to create new norms or to
you know to create to set norms for a particular group of people. Right, right and and we've lost that
sense of something written as a monument because now you know I could go and self-publish something
on the internet. You know and right. It's really people cared. They could all you know
I'm not afraid of tomorrow.
So, like the printed word has gotten kind of cheap.
It wasn't cheap in the ancient world.
Yeah. But so there's also means that that we see this throughout ancient
Newer Eastern and even even into late antiquity to a certain extent in
paganism where you have a class of priests whose job is essentially to be
able to read. Yeah to read read the stories as part of these ritual experiences
that people have. Yeah they're supposed to maintain the documents copy the
documents be able to
read the documents, be able to know how to perform the rituals.
So this starts out as just knowledge that's handed down
orally, but then once it goes into written form,
then you get lector priests in Egypt,
you get the priests who are in charge
of the sibling books in Rome, where their job is
to be able to consult the books.
To consult the things written, to know how to do these things.
But again, it's not about...
you know, here's a set of truths that are to be believed. It's not about even
here's like some hidden knowledge about the universe, right, in elevation. It's
that, that here's the correct procedure, right? Here's the correct way to do this.
It's how it's the correct way to tell the story, the correct way to do the ritual,
right? The correct application of these things, right? And the sibling books are
a really good example of that, because that's literally what it was.
They would go something would happen, you know, there's a comment, oh, that's a bad omen. What do we do?
Well, we went and consulted the books and the books said we should bury three slaves alive. This is an actual example that happened.
Yeah, right. And so they go and they do that. And they're like, well, okay, right? So it was this very procedural kind of thing.
Yeah, notice it's never bury three senators alive.
No.
And if it was, they probably would have...
if you know, named a slave as a senator and then buried him alive.
Or a horse if we're colligula, you know.
So, and we're not.
We're not used to now thinking of the Torah this way.
Sure.
But if you read the Torah for itself and you read it in that ancient context, the Torah really
is sort of the same thing.
There's countless examples of this, but sort of exhibit A of this is Passover.
Right?
Where?
Right.
You have, it's even given, right, it's laid out first.
Here's how you are to celebrate the Passover in Exodus, and it gives all of the ritual instructions
for celebrating the Passover every year.
This is to be your first of month, so it even starts constructing a ritual calendar, right?
All of that information comes first.
And then the actual event of the Passover happens afterwards.
Yeah, that's
That's why the Bible doesn't make a really good screenplay kind of as written.
You're like, wait, let's take a moment here.
Yes, certainly there's death instruction about to come, but we're going to first describe
this ritual to you and how you're going to do it for the future because it's not a play
by play of what happened.
It's a text within a ritual context.
So of course, those ritual instructions are there.
And our primary, you know, you're going to do these ritual acts and then you're going
to tell the story.
your family and you're going to participate in the story in this way. Oh, by the way,
here's the story. Right. After the fact. Right. And we've mentioned before on the
show, I know that you see that same pattern with Christ's mystical supper, that the Eucharist
is actually instituted, ritually before Christ dies and rises again. Yeah. Do this as my
remembrance. This is my body, my blood, which again, if you just take it as a
a sort of screenplay doesn't make much sense.
Like you're not dead Lord.
What are you talking about?
You know?
The body has not been broken yet.
Your blood has not been shed yet.
Right, right.
Even though he puts it in the present tense, you know,
or past tense really, this is my body broken.
This is my blood shed.
Yeah, so, but this is, I mean, this is true
over and over again in the Torah, right?
So this is even true, I mean, chapter one
in the beginning of chapter two, right?
Creation is put into this seven days.
structure and the story of the creation of the world culminates with therefore the Sabbath
day, the Sabbath day of the week is holy and you don't do any work.
And right and and Sabbath is not just a name for the day of the week.
It's a specific set of practices that you engage in.
Right.
And that's there explicitly.
So it's not so if you take that at face value, it's not saying like here's here's a
what you have to believe precisely in terms of the exact order of events when God created
the world.
The thrust of it is, therefore, you should rest on the seventh day of the week as a way
of participating in God's enthronement over his creation and his rule.
And there's the actual event of the giving of the covenant at Sinai and Pentecost, the
annual observance. Right so that
Even these narrative portions are directly connected
then to the ritual, which involves the telling of the story,
the participation in the story.
And of course, there's countless examples.
It's not just the Torah.
The Book of Esther is all aimed at the celebration of Purim.
Arguably, first Maccabees is all aimed
at the Feast of Light, Sikhanaka.
Right.
So that's sort of one type.
So that sort of parallel to the way
that like the enuméalish functioned,
that there was this ritual, this annual ritual,
there was a regular ritual observance
in which the story was enacted and participated in.
More like the Egyptian book of the dead
and the actual rights instructions,
you get a book like Leviticus.
Right, which is clearly a liturgical book
That's mostly about this is how you do these rich.
And that's brought out by the title.
That's the Greek title.
The Vitykos is literally the
the Vittical thing, the Levi's thing.
Yeah, the book of the Levi's.
Yeah. The thing here being a book.
But yeah. Now that's not the Hebrew title.
The Hebrew title is Vahikre.
But that's one of those titles that's sort of like
the things we don't translate in our book.
the things we don't translate in our
or orthodox liturgical books, right?
Like the Kuthismata, right?
Because that sounds fancy.
That's the things you can sit during.
Yeah, it just means it's only a bit there.
So it's like Vahekre, that sounds really interesting.
That means, and he called, it's just the first word
of the book of Leviticus.
Right, I think that's through all the Torah books, right?
The Hebrew names are just the first word
that you see on the scroll.
Right, but so the Greek name tells you
like the actual context, like what this is, right?
And what it is, the book of Leviticus is a manual for priests, basically.
Right.
And some of that's obvious.
So a big chunk of Leviticus is this detailed stuff of, here's how you divvy up the entrails
of this type of sacrifice.
Here are the things that you offer for this, that type of sacrifice.
Yeah.
And a lot of it's super repetitive.
Here's what you do with the fatty lobe that is next to the liver.
Like that kind of detail, you know.
Right.
you
Yeah, so that very much reads like a priest manual.
That reads like rubrics, like instructions, right?
Yeah.
Now there's other parts of it that don't necessarily
read that way to us, especially since we're used to having this in our modern English
called the law, right?
So there's a lot of it, like in the holiness code that runs from Vitica's 17 to somewhere
around 23 or 24 depending on who you ask.
it looks to us like it's just a
bunch of like moral rules, right? Like,
Leviticus 18 is all rules about sexual morality.
Yeah.
And immorality, right?
And so that seems to us to be less directed towards
a priest, right? We think, well, no, that's like so people could read it
and know what they should and shouldn't do morally, right?
So the problem with that is nobody could read.
And they didn't have access to the text, even if they could, right?
they could, right?
because there were so few copies that they were treasured and the priests had
possession of them. So the way people had access to what was in those texts was
through the priests, right? They would come and participate in the rituals and
in the feasts and in the sacrifices and when they came and participated, right?
So this would be sort of mediated to them through the text and through the
priest, right? That's how they found out about it. So those commandments were
and they were not just in there for-
the priest to sort of advise people, right? Though obviously or it should be
obvious and hopefully priests were doing that though we know from reading the
Old Testament that that was not necessarily the case most of the time. They
should have been teaching people you know what to avoid and what not to do. But
for the most part those sins are in there because the priest has to know what to
do about them when they happen.
Remember, the priest job, the job that this is a manual for, right?
The priest there in, whether it's in the camp, in the wilderness, whether it's in the temple later in Judah,
their job is to maintain purity through the sacrificial system, to manage the sin in the camp or in the nation, so that God can safely remain living among them.
Yeah, so it's not just a list of like, here's things you're supposed to do and not do.
It's okay this bad thing happened so here's what we do about that
Right here's how we restore justice here's how we
What the sacrifices we need to offer here's the kind of repentance that needs to be seen if there's not repentance
Here's what you have to do in terms of stoning somebody or and even and even like the narrative bits of Leviticus
I mean the you know the probably in my mind the classic example being the institution of the day of atonement ritual is
is given in response.
to one of the narrative parts of Leviticus in which Nadob and Abihu really mess up and
God kills them. You know, fire comes out from the Lord and kills them there in the Tabernacle.
So that's given, and this is why we do the Day of Atomot stuff in response to that,
so that kind of thing doesn't happen again.
Yeah, we know what that to recur, right?
That's yeah, like there's a little sign with a number they hang up so many days since
death by holiness, right? You want to get that number high? We want to keep it rolling.
Yeah, and so therefore, you know, those parts are also sort of a priest manual, but they're a priest manual for managing, right, the sins of the people.
And dealing with that because that's sort of part of their job, right? And we of course have sort of direct parallels to that in manuals of confession in the Orthodox Church, right?
where the
These aren't like commandments, right?
You don't hand one of these manuals of confession.
You shouldn't.
If you're a layperson in the Orthodox Church,
do not buy or read a Byzantine manual of confession.
It is not for you.
That is a, yeah.
Yeah.
It's like spiritual web MD, man.
If right, you will excommunicate yourself.
I mean, we're not forbidding people from reading books,
just saying like, look, you don't need that book.
That is not right.
It's not for, I mean, it's not,
It's...
It's not supposed to be applied by laymen to themselves.
That's what we're talking about.
You're not going to have a good time.
No, that's what I'm saying.
It seems like fun in games, but it's not.
It's like WebMD convinces everyone they have cancer
and they're going to die.
So this is the same kind of thing, but spiritually.
So don't read it.
But the purpose of that is for especially someone
who's new to hearing confessions from people
to give advice on here's how to counsel someone dealing
with this or that or the other.
and here the more serious.
forms of this and here are the less serious forms of this.
Not that you disregard them, but you have to be more strict,
right, with the more severe ones,
with someone who's committing those,
than with someone who's, you know,
could have the less severe forms.
So it's practical advice for priests
who are hearing confessions, right?
It's not for someone to sit and try
and hear their own confession, just like WebMD, right?
You go to your doctor and let your doctor diagnose you, right?
Right, so that's the idea there.
So again, that's not used to how we're thinking about the TORR functioning, but that is
really how it functioned and how it was received by people in the ancient Near East who
were used to text functioning that way within communities.
Well, and it continues on, right?
I mean, we're going to kind of make our way chronologically down as we so often do.
like something that
much more recent. If you pick up the like the liturgy con that is published by the Antioch
Archdiocese that you and I serve in, right up at the front is the list of commandments
of St. Basil the Great to priests. Now the book is mostly a book of how to do vespers and
or throws some of the divine liturgy in all these services, right, you know, as I say,
you know, say the black do the red, right, because the spoken parts are in black ink and
and the-
actions are in red ink, which is where the word rubric comes from.
It has to do with red.
But you've got these from a script people.
But you've got them.
It's not in.
Yeah.
Sorry.
Actually, the rubric bit being about red is improv.
No, oh, sorry, very meta there.
But but there's these commandments from St. Basil.
For instance, one of them is never stand at the synoxies.
that's gathering together for the...
the Church Service. Never stand at the synoxies having hatred toward anyone so it's not to
banish the Comforter. And so this is a commandment to priests, like don't go to, you know, don't
serve angry, basically, because that's bad for this. So it's a, it's a, it's a, it comes
off as a moral commandment, but it's a moral commandment in service to ritual. Right. So this
This is, you know, even till today we have the same kind of use of texts.
But as we switch into or move into Deuteronomy,
so Deuteronomy there's this shift
because Deuteronomy is presented here
this is Moses giving his sort of final instructions
to Israel before they enter the land.
And so as things are repeated here
as the name Deuteronomy implies,
there's a little bit of a shift in that now
This is aimed at, here's how we're going to implement these things.
Now that we're not in a camp in the wilderness anymore.
Now we're in, now we're going to be in the land, right?
So people have fits by people, I mean Old Testament scholars who are still people.
Even the 19th century German ones.
Old Testament scholars are people too?
that the
The instructions are different in Leviticus than they are in Deuteronomy.
Right.
For Passover.
Or Exodus Deuteronomy for Passover.
Right.
It's like, yeah, because one's out in the desert.
One is in a city.
Yeah.
The surgical change, adapting to the particular needs of the context.
It's okay.
It's okay, everybody.
But so one major element is that in the same way that we see these things functioning.
with the priesthood, like in Leviticus,
we start to see in Deuteronomy more talk of the elders,
the presbyters of the people,
because as we talked about back in the priesthood episode,
these get separated, priesthood and sort of elderhood,
that the, I don't wanna use civil and religious,
because that's not a thing.
Not a thing.
Right, right.
But those two things get separate, right?
The king and the high priest are two different people, right? Moses and Aaron, right?
And the Levites and the elders of the people. We've talked about this in the priesthood episode,
right? So they're still separate. But so the elders and then the king, right, get talked
about in the same terms by Deuteronomy, where as it's presented in Deuteronomy, this is
the Torah as sort of a tool or instrument, right? The king is to make a copy of the Torah
and study it, for them to use.
to guide the people to establish justice, right, to deal with disputes, to deal with sins
when they happen in reconciliation and repentance, right.
And so-
Very practical, not just a theoretical, here's some things we believe and have to agree
with.
Right.
And so-
This is what needs to be done.
That word law, again, that we've gotten hammered with, right, thanks a lot, Saint
Jerome.
I actually have his icon here, so I actually like Saint Jerome.
But because you know, you don't have a line as a pet.
You're not as cool as him.
It is true.
I do not have a line as a pet.
Right.
We're used to looking at the Torah as if it's a law code.
And you'll even see this in some of these intro
to the Old Testament books where they go, oh, well,
Well this is the law, this is the Jewish law.
We're going to compare it to homerabi's code
right
homerabi our Amorite friend
And he was a giant I just really he's an Amorite so he's one of those clan
Oh, yeah, and he had this great affection for sandals imported from Crete
Right I remember that yeah, yeah
Yeah, yeah, huh.
This was a little bit of a close horse.
I never made that connection that-
He was an amurite, that's a wow.
He's one of the Amurru.
So, but a law code functions differently.
And this is even, shall we say, misunderstanding
is even built into some theological systems,
where the Torah gets turned into law,
and God is the king, and he gives this law that must be obeyed
or he will punish.
And in actuality,
This use of the text and this function of the text that we've been describing that's apparent in the Torah is not really a law code.
It's actually more like what's sometimes called an English household law.
Right. And they call it household law because it's, they're working off of the Greek term,
or a Mia, right?
Right.
You can amix mean something else in English.
So yeah.
Yeah.
I mean, literally, if you're going to translate that word, it's sort of the law of the house.
Well, or the customs of the house.
The way is the house.
Household management is probably the way.
This is how we do things in this household, right?
And that's how we resolve disputes, and this is how it is governed.
As long as you live under my roof, dot dot dot.
And so if we don't understand that, there's big chunks of St. Paul's epistles that we're
we're going to radically misinterpret because he uses this concept of the household of God.
over and over again. And he especially uses it when he's talking about the
prespitors in the church and what they do. And the episcopy, the bishops, as we
would say, the leadership in the church, they are managers of the household of
God. He's directly appealing to this language. And we hear that in English and
because we're so you
to law, right? This law code thinking, we think that's something other than, and different
from what was going on in the Torah, right? When really what St. Paul is saying is, is
thoroughly consistent, right? He's saying that the prespitors of the new covenant in the
church have pretty much the same job as the prespitors, the elders of the people, in
the old covenant.
Right, they also were really managing that household.
So, we talked just now about sort of priests and how sort of the Torah worked in terms
of them as an instrument and we talked about the king and the elders of the people.
So there's somebody from a couple of weeks ago who we haven't talked about yet.
Yeah, how about the prophets?
I mean, where did they fit into all of this?
I mean, they're not walking around with texts in their hands and applying them to people.
Right.
So we don't see like Saint Elias, you know, the prophet Elijah going in, you know, in front of King Ahab
and unrolling Atoris girl and like reading him this section about what is to be done with false prophets.
Right. Right. Like that's not what we see. Right. We don't even see like, I mean, Ezekiel
was from a priestly family and, you know, therefore presumably can read it right. We don't even see
him doing that. We see him wandering around naked and stuff. Right? We see him doing
prophetic, and it was our prophetic actions, having visions, right? And so they're not using
the Torah instrumentally, at least we don't see them doing that in the same way that priest
and king or priest and pressmener do in the Old Testament.
Yeah, so they're not really quoting it usually even, are they?
Right, no, now what they're saying is consonant with...
it. Right, right. It's consistent. Right. But they're not showing up and quoting it. Right.
Now our 19th century German friends would say that's because it hasn't been written yet, but we're
not going to get into all that right now. But they don't. Right. And so the idea here is that
is related to where the Torah came from. Right. And what it is. Right. So
So, most of this goes to...
the top of Mount Sinai and as we've talked about before,
enters into the divine council, right?
The law is given through angels, right?
He speaks to God face to face.
We've talked about how this is Christ, right?
And so he has this direct experience
and direct encounter with God
as we talked about in the last episode about prophets, right?
And then he brings the Torah,
which means teaching in Hebrew.
He brings this.
teaching and the teaching therefore serves as the sort of mediation of Moses' experience
for the people.
Remember the people are terrified.
They see that God is on the mountain.
They're not going near it.
When they see Moses' faces all shining, they're like cover up Moses.
It's a really a traumatic thing for them.
They're not interested in that direct encounter with God.
Right, and so the Torah comes in this
mediatorial role.
between this direct experience, which they can't handle.
And this is not just some kind of psychological weakness.
Death by holiness is a real thing.
This is something they can't abide, because they haven't been purified for it.
And therefore, there is this teaching that functions mediaturally.
This is by the way, why when we
read in Jeremiah and Ezekiel and Joel about the coming of the Holy Spirit in the new covenant.
This is why we get this element of you will not have a man will not have to teach his brother
right to do this and not to do this because the law will be written on their heart.
Right so direct experience that they will also be having now. Right and so once
Once a person has been purified.
by the blood of Christ, they are able to experience God directly. That takes the form of the filling of the Holy Spirit.
And so now they don't need the Torah in this instrumental role anymore.
That doesn't mean that the Torah is no longer valid, because the Torah is still the description of that experience.
Right.
So nobody who has this direct experience with God is going to be a law breaker, or if they
are they're going to end up like an anisons of fire.
Right. Right. So that's still real. But that's why that that that mediation is no longer necessary
because now we can all we can all approach. But so for that same reason the profits in the
old testament didn't need the Torah in that mediatorial or instrumental role. Yeah. They didn't need it.
it was not secondhand. I mean secondhand sounds negative but I mean it was direct.
for them. So they're like, yeah, I don't need you to tell me what God said because I know
him. Right. And so they could. So Saint Elias, Prophet Elijah, can come to Ahab and because
of his direct encounters with God, right, he could come to Ahab and denounce his wickedness,
right? And pronounce the judgment of God against him without needing to like cite or proof
text, right? Because he knows who God is. And wherever this is, the core is this is
Christ.
Right. So, but the important element to carry forward, right, is that even when the Torah is
serving this instrumental role, the authority is never in the text itself. Right. Because if it were,
then prophets having direct experiences would not, you know, sort of Trump, it's not Trump,
but they would have to be citing the Bible.
they could not simply say, look, let's say at the Lord, because he said this to me,
it would always have to make some reference to the text, because that if that's where the authority is.
But rather, the text points to an experience, and if you're having that experience,
then you're also accessing the actual authority which is God Himself.
Right, and so this is, God Himself sends the authority, Christ maintains the authority.
Right? The text is mediation.
to allow a person to draw close and have the direct experience of God in Christ.
And this is when we talk about the formation of rabbinic Judaism,
that what makes it very different than the religion of ancient Israel and of second-temple Judaism,
this is the big shift. The authority goes to the text itself.
you no longer have a succession of profits, you have a succession.
of scribes who read and interpret and apply the text. Right? Yeah. And I don't want to
be mean to our Protestant friends. But honestly a lot of forms of Protestantism are following
that model. Yeah. Show me where it is in the Bible. Right. Of we're going to be biblical scribes.
right? Reading it interprets the text. Which I mean, we should say by no means are we
suggesting a kind of denigration of the scripture. I mean, we've been talking about this stuff
for almost two years now and mainly talking about the Bible. So, you know, I clearly
don't care about the Bible, I think it's a point. Right? Exactly. I will show you my student loan
balance, sir. There you go. They had a house anyway. Right. But it's, but we're talking about a different
Mo
of how it's received and used and talked about and that sort of thing.
Right. Right. That it is the text of Scripture points to someone greater than
itself. Right. Right. And that is Christ. And so the authority is never in the
text itself. It's always Christ who is mediated through the text. Right. And Christ
is not mediated through every text. Right. So this is why it's not
denigrating the script.
Christ is not mediated through Moabie Dick.
Right. He's not even through weathering heights.
It's not even when Patrick Stewart recites passages from it.
I mean, especially when Patrick Stewart recites passages.
Now if William Shatner or when Ricardo Montelbaum recites passages from it, then we're talking.
The
Right, so, you know, weathering heights, pick your text, right?
The experience of, the direct experience of God in Christ is not mediated through any
of those texts, right?
And again, I don't want to be mean, but this is one of my problems with those, the gospel
according to fill in the pop culture thing here, books.
Right?
This is how old I am.
I remember.
the gospel according to the Simpsons.
Oh, I remember that back of the day.
Yeah, yeah.
There were a bunch of those back of the night
as gospel according to the ex files,
the gospel according to Star Trek, the next generation, right?
None of those,
none of those pop culture probably,
they're all fine to enjoy as entertainment.
They do not mediate Christ to people
the way the scriptures do.
They're not preaching the gospel.
And to be fair,
most of the people at least who write those books,
some of
them are probably writing it as a crass caching. But I think most of the good people who write those books
aren't intending to put them in parallel with the scriptures, right? No. But it almost conveys that.
Right. Right. The idea that you could just sort of get the gospel anywhere, right? Just be
dated through trees, right? It's be dated through Marvel movies. It's right. And that does serve to
lower the level of scripture because
you know, guess what? There's a lot of people who find that pop culture stuff more entertaining
than reading the Bible. Well, that's because it's entertainment. And you kind of give them
an excuse. You know, yeah. Right. No, no, see this is good. This has good Christian moral
lessons in it. You know, and, and yeah, you know, if you're a kid and you're trying to
get your parents to let you watch stuff, okay, you know, game recognized game, but that's
It's not the highest mode of discourse, so we say.
Right, right, exactly.
So yeah, so okay, well, all of that in hand, I mean, at some point this stuff starts getting
written down.
So yeah, like when exactly does that occur?
Because it's clear that, like it's clear that you have the community of Israel exists
before these texts exist, right?
So at some point it gets written down.
Where's that all coming from?
And this writing starts at a certain point in human history,
which regardless of how old and again,
not interested in discussing it,
how old you think the earth is,
it's still a long time passes before any of this
starts getting written down.
So obviously the first thing traditionally
that starts getting written down is the Torah.
Right.
The five books of Moses.
Right the Pentateuch right, but you know
Again we're gonna have to have a talk here people
Gather up children. I know
People have been taught the traditional shorthand and it is a traditional shorthand
Moses wrote the Torah right or Moses wrote the Pentateuch
But we have to take a little more nuanced right when we look at reality
if we had a-
little more nuanced, this is so for example the earliest form of the the Torah we have available to us which is the Dead Sea Scrolls right?
Is written in a language in an alphabet in a language that didn't exist when when Moses left?
Yeah, it didn't exist in his era and you know and even if I can imagine there's probably someone out there that was saying you know
Yes, it did. It's just what academics say, but there's internal indications about this too like
a good example, for instance, is that the Torah includes the death and then the funeral
of Moses.
Right.
So, unless you could pull out the, well, he's a prophet.
He prophesied his own death.
Right.
But it's not presented that way.
It's like, he doesn't say, and this is the manner in which I will die.
And this is the manner in which I will be buried.
You know, it's not, it's just there.
And this is not to deny that Moses engaged in scribal activity.
There are portions of the Torah.
I'm specifically thinking of Exodus 15 and the song of the sea and Deuteronomy 32.
Yeah.
That in their current form, go back to the mosaic era.
Right.
Meaning they haven't been updated, really.
That's why they're so hard to read in Translate.
Yeah.
Because they're...
This is...
These are the only samples we have of that sort of paleo Hebrew.
Right.
Translator
but not really translated.
And there are parts of Deuteronomy 32
where if you compare English translations,
they are wildly different.
Yeah, because even the best scholars are looking at it
and kind of going, well, I think that's what this is.
Right.
So there is, so it is more appropriate
in terms of being accurate to reality,
to talk about the mosaic origin of the peniting.
Right that the first
of what becomes the Pentateuch as we have it now, right? That's where that
urlayer is, right? And then over time that gets translated, it gets edited, it
gets, you know, moved into a different alphabet, right? It gets translated into
Greek, right? And a Greek translation that is no less authoritative, right? than
the Hebrew. And sometimes you can actually see by looking at the text,
Not just stuff like Moses's death and funeral, but you can see the editing process become
apparent in the text, right?
There's stuff that's anachronistic.
Right.
You know, the story that we read at Vespers in the Orthodox Church before most of the
feast days of the Holy Fathers about Abram going and rescuing his nephew Lot in the original
the word of the five kings.
the the battle is as the Abram Abram
pursues
Them as far as Dan
Right, well that city was not called Dan in Abrams time
Right, because Dan is the name of one of the 12 tribes of Israel
Right, and it wasn't even it wasn't even called Dan when Moses lived
Right, right? We find out how it gets the name Dan at the end of the book of Joshua when the tribe of Dan goes and conquers it
even though they weren't supposed to do it.
and rename it before that it was called layish.
So somebody through the centuries came and updated that place
name because nobody knows where layish was anymore.
We've been calling it Dan for a while now.
So let's just update that for Dan.
So people will know where we're talking about when we tell
the story.
So in the same way that if you read a story
about pre-Columbian American history.
Right.
As I know everyone here does.
Everyone listen.
But they'll say, you know, these, this tribe traveled up the Missouri River and settled near
St. Louis, right?
They're not implying that the tribe called it the Missouri River and that St. Louis was
there.
Right.
It was like a Native American city.
Yeah.
It's the modern, right.
They're just saying, this is the modern location that we all know.
Right.
But if they use the native names for those places, then all of us modern people.
reading it would be like where? Yeah, they have no idea. Like, you know, for instance, if you were to
translate Julius Caesar's Gallic Wars and to make this kind of reference, you would begin with,
you know, all of France is divided into four parts, whatever it is, rather than all Gauls, sorry,
yeah, three. I should, I've read enough asterix in Oblix comics that I should remember that.
Right. Well, just just remember what Aristotle told us. Everything that comes in three is perfect.
Are you saying Francis?
No. No, it didn't come in three. It was split in three. He was perfected.
We love you French listeners though. We do.
But so and there's places where that's even more transparent. We'll where it'll give a name of a
place and then say which used to be called something else right right and there are places in the
the Torah that say something that says,
until this very day.
Yeah. Right.
So if Moses is writing.
this like a year and a half after it happened until this very day doesn't make you
know right not that big of a deal right this stone that we set up last week is
still there to this very day right so that that implies that that's like an
editorial note right from later right where they're copying it and and they're
like oh yeah that stone's still there to this very day right so they noted it
you know hey reader you can go and see this stone from this story I just told you
Right. So the question, when was the Torah written? The answer is several centuries.
Right. Starting somewhere in the mid-second millennium BC. And again, I'm not going to argue about
the date of the Exodus. And then going through until after the exile, when you know,
So sometime around the time of Ezra it probably received its current form.
The Hebrew received it's pretty much its current form.
And then of course the Greek translation was made after that.
Other translations were made after that.
And there are, when we take a look at the other books of the Old Testament,
we see similar things. These aren't books that someone sat down one day
and wrote in Toto.
and they definitely aren't books that were written like
as the things were happening. Yeah right.
The book of Joshua is not his journal, right,
like from during the conquest.
Today we marched around Jericho, dear diary.
Right. That's not how any of this works.
Right. But you especially see this in some of the books
because of the themes, right? So judges and
and Ruth originally circulated on the same scroll.
And...
The book of Judges, when you read it closely, and you're looking for the arc, right?
The arc of the book.
What the arc of the book is is you have this repeated refrain in that those days there
was no cave.
There was no king in Israel.
Everyone did what was right in their own eyes, right?
It's about the tribes descending into chaos, right?
The last four chapters that nobody reads, there's this huge civil war between the tribes
where they're killing each other, right?
And so it's saying, this is why we need it.
to stop stuff like this from happening. And then if you read those last four chapters closely,
again, right, suspiciously, the tribe of Benjamin are the bad guys and Judah are the good guys.
Whatever I mean by good guys and bad guys, well as we've said before, this isn't doing modern
history. This isn't trying to be objective. Yeah. Right. It's like here's a list of complaints of
this tribe over against the other tribe. And really, the blame was shared by... There's none of that,
Right? No both sides thing going on.
Here are the many factors that led to this civil war, economic and otherwise.
Right?
So it's giving a clear perspective.
Benjamin being Saul's tribe, Judah being David's tribe.
And then on the scroll as appended, this story about David's great grandma.
Yeah, Ruth.
That's what the scroll ends with.
So it's very clear what's going on here in Judges and Ruth.
talking about the importance of the Davidic monarchy.
Yeah, this is this is how we got to that to the point that we needed a king and how like we let's support the kingship because we don't want things to be like that
You know why it's the king is the right one right not false yeah, and
You know we also hold that the Divinig Walnutke is very important of course because it produces the Messiah
Yes, right as we have said many times before yeah and and
And we see the same thing when you look at what are in the Greek, the four books of kingdoms,
what are first and second Samuel, first and second kings, right, and other translations.
You see this is one overarching narrative explaining from the perspective of the exile how Israel
ended up getting destroyed and Judah ended up being taken into exile and why.
Right.
So things start out good with the Divinic monarchy and then they go very bad.
And they follow
was basically prophesied in Deuteronomy through Moses.
Yeah, once you get into the land, this is what's going to happen and you're going to end up
in exile.
Right?
So it's showing that unfold.
Right.
It's not just a historical, it's not a chronicle.
You know, there are chronicles, right?
The books of chronicles.
But it's not just a chronicle saying this happened and then this happened and this happened.
There is, like you said, an arc to it.
Right.
And they keep referring you to the annals.
else is king.
consult the annals. Yeah, it's not written in the chronicles of the books of the
King the two. I know it's over and over again in those books. Yeah, so you've got
that. If you want to go read the official record, right, we're here making a
point. Right. So not that those official records were objective either, those
were from the King's point of view. So, right. But so then, you know, that's
that's two two of our parts of the old testament, the other part being the
the writings of the writing.
is just this giant catch-all, right? The writings are sort of like all the other stuff that's in the old testament.
So you have things from like Ezra and Niha Maya that are from right after the return from exile,
all the way up to the Book of Wisdom, or this is going to make people mad too.
The Church Fathers were fully aware that the Book of Wisdom was not written by Solomon.
Even though it's sometimes called the wisdom of Solomon.
Yeah, because aren't the earliest sort of references to it as being canonical?
Don't they include it in the New Testament?
Yes. The earliest references we have to it being included in the canon have it as part of the New Testament
because they knew it was written in Greek and they knew it was written in the first century AD.
It was probably written in the early 30s of the first century AD.
If we're going to be modern about it, it's the wisdom inspired by Solomon.
Right, right, right, right.
Sort of all the wisdom literature gets associated with Solomon, right?
Yeah.
Because he's so good.
Because I know there's people out there who, if I said, was Proverbs written by Solomon,
you probably off the cuff really quickly say yes, and then I'd go through and show you
like, oh really?
Because this chapter says it's the wisdom of this other guy.
Right.
But we still ascribe Proverbs to Solomon.
Just like the Psalms get ascribed to David, even though, again, the Psalms don't say
they're all written by David.
Some of them say they're written by other people.
the sons of Korah or the son of Acef or Moses or other people. So yeah, so that, that
I think is pretty clearly the latest one. That's the only one that was written AD.
Right. Of the of the Old Testament books. Arguably the only one that was originally written
in Greek. There's argument about some of the macabre books of the macapies, depending
Okay, including right like
was probably written in Greek, but then, you know, I'm not Russian, so. But you get the point,
right? So those are written over this vast, this vast lot of time. So there's not these sort of,
in all of these discussions, people tend to take what they know about the New Testament and then
generalize it and just act like it's true of the Old Testament, but it really isn't.
Yeah, because they're all down New Testament books, right? Right.
most
Most of them, there is a clear author that there's every good reason actually to believe
that it came pretty directly from that author.
And especially because the New Testament books, they're writing, and then they're, I mean,
we'll get to this, right?
But they're writing and their collection happens really fast by compared to the Old Testament,
right?
You know, where the Old Testament we were talking about centuries upon centuries, the New
Testament, it's pretty much wrapped up almost in a bow within about 70 or 80 or so years,
Right.
Right, right. And we can nail down pretty, I mean, pretty sure Galatians was written about
45 or pretty sure. We can go down pretty solid dates. Like you can't do that with the
old testament books. Yeah. And a lot of it is because, I mean, some of it, of course,
is because there's indications within the texts that point to things that we have other
corroborating evidence for particular historical events or where someone was at a particular
time.
You know.
And so, and that's just because records from that period are much, much better.
You know, we have a lot more to work with than, you know, if you're looking at
1500 years of
ancient Near Eastern history. Well, there's less, there's less process.
Right. Right. So we don't end up
five centuries after
Jeremiah lived with two
to pretty radically different versions of the book of Jeremiah.
We have that for Jeremiah, but we don't have that with any of the new testament books.
Right. It's pretty much the same text just about.
Right. Almost every copy.
Yeah. There's a couple of exceptions, like Luke and Acts.
But even those, you're talking about the biggest difference we have is about 10%.
Right. We don't have radically different versions of books,
like, or the different versions we have in the book of Daniel, or the different versions we have in
of the book of faster.
So what happens is that the Hebrew Bible or
and the Christian Old Testament, which are technically different things.
Just sort of emerge out of ancient history,
and they emerge from a process.
They aren't a series of books that are written down by different people at these specific points in time,
and then I'll get wrapped up together in a book.
And notably the church fathers don't ever treat them that way.
No, they knew all this stuff.
Because that's how that's how religious text
It's worked.
Right.
So, you know, and so we talked in the episode about how to and how not to read the Bible about
the whole modernist, fundamentalist controversy and all of these things.
And we have folks who are now especially in sort of the Anglophone, English-speaking Orthodox,
world who come from those backgrounds, right?
And so there's still a little bit of the
reactionary idea and so there's some people who seem to feel like they need to
like be more conservative than the church fathers. Right so you get people
wanting to argue against all reality that you know Moses wrote every word of
the Torah as we have it today. Right and like if you actually read what the
church fathers say about it like a good portion of them a good portion of them
because they had read for Ezra.
They'd read the epistle of Barnabas,
they'd read other tax that contained this tradition.
A good portion of them thought that Israel,
actually Israel lost the Torah
and that Ezra miraculously recreated it
so that it comes from Ezra.
And they'll make offhand comments about it.
St. Jerome does that at one point.
Yeah, which, we're not,
now don't get us wrong.
We're not saying that that is how it happened,
but we are pointing out that some of the fathers see that.
Right.
Right, and so they didn't have to sit there and say,
no, every word of the Torah, as we have it now in Greek or Latin,
right?
Or even as the Hebrew that was floating around at the time, right?
Because there were people in the ancient church, right?
Who could read Hebrew?
St. Jerome was one of them, right?
Right.
Or maybe not so well, but he could.
And they don't feel the need to say that, right?
St. Jerome literally says, like whether you think what we have is what Moses wrote
whether you think Ezra restored it.
This is what it says.
Right, this is our text.
So, yeah.
Right, so then the question is like.
And he actually said that, he said that in reference to,
let me make this very pointed,
he said that in reference to the phrase
until this very day, as it appears in the Torah.
So he was saying that it was a common opinion
at the time that
until this very day was Ezra's editorial comment.
And meant until the day of Ezra.
Interesting.
So he was saying this could be until the day of Moses,
this could be until the day of Ezra.
So this kind of raises the question
then I mean, do we know who wrote any of the Old Testament?
Who actually was the person who wrote it down?
Do we know that?
know that particular word.
that we have now? No. Right. No. I mean, there's some cases where we have no idea. Right.
We have no idea who wrote first through fourth kingdoms. Yeah. Because, you know, again,
if you say that the prophet Samuel wrote the first two of those books, you have to deal with the
fact that he dies in the first one. Well, yeah. And if good listener, if anyone comes to you and says,
traditionally.
Samuel wrote first and second Samuel. I want you to respond to them. By traditionally, you mean the Talmud
is that where it comes from?
So which is not Orthodox Christian tradition. Right, and that makes sense because everybody reading
it in Greek, it wasn't called Samuel. Right, those were the kingdoms for the first and second kingdoms.
But so we have no idea. We have no idea who wrote first and second chronicles. We don't have a hint.
Right.
As we said, is the origin of the Torah, right?
But especially if you get outside of Exodus 15
and Deuteronomy 32, right?
Is this the exact word that Moses would have written?
Well, no, it's not the exact word
because it's in a different language, right?
And very least it would have been spelled differently,
and written in a different alphabet, right?
But here's the thing, it doesn't matter.
Yeah.
It does it literally does not
matter. It has no bearing on the authority of the Bible in the church who wrote it and
went. Because all of this works. Yeah, it could have all been written by me last week.
Wouldn't make a lick of difference. Which would be consistent with how much you sleep. So
yeah. Fair enough. So and we'll explain why in our second head. Yeah, exactly. All right,
Well, all of that said, we're gonna take...
a little more break and we'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on
the next part of the Lord of Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF Radio.
Are you curious about the Orthodox Christian faith?
Do you have questions about Orthodox Christianity
that you can't trust strangers in internet forums to answer?
Are you an Orthodox Christian looking for a reliable first place
to send your interested friends?
Do you need help finding an Orthodox church near you?
My name is Father Paul Hodge.
I serve in the Antiochian Orthodox Christian Archdiocese
of North America.
My name is Father Joseph Lucas.
I serve in the orthodox church in America.
My name is Father Anthony Cook.
I serve in the Greek Orthodox Archdiocese of America.
And I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick,
Chief Content Officer of Ancient Faith Ministries
and a priest of the Antioch in Archdiocese.
And we're the Orthodox Intro Team.
If you're looking for a first stop online
to get an introduction to the Orthodox faith,
a place to get answers to questions
from qualified Orthodox Christian clergy,
a place to send your friends
and not just toss them into the chaos.
of the Internet.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and
Father Stephen DeYoung. If you have a question call now at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back everybody. Like I said, we're not actually taking calls tonight,
despite what you just heard the voice of Steve say. But maybe if they call in,
in right then and there was
watching on the stream, right?
That will cause the room where the phone is
to slowly fade into view.
And they'll see the ringing phone by itself.
Right?
You're going to hold David Lynch thing.
Yeah, yeah.
I was going to say twilight zone sort of thing.
Yeah, I mean, it was funny.
I remember last time, right?
That sort of the stream started out
with the camera inside the studio there in Chesterton.
Where there wasn't anybody, it was automated over there.
It was kind of funny.
Did Father Joseph Lucas give you that background music by the way?
It's very kind of Miami. No, no. I picked that out. No, yeah, I picked that out.
Actually myself but yes, yes. Yeah, he is there in Miami. They've got alligators and stuff and very good Cuban coffee.
So everything I know about Miami, I learned from the Will Smith song.
I don't know a lot about Miami.
Right.
Worth going, the food is excellent.
Among us.
So yeah, all right. Well, welcome back. It is the second half.
We just wrapped up by saying it doesn't matter who wrote the books, particularly of the Old Testament or when
in terms of like the rock
Like the it doesn't matter what your name is can you do that? No, I you know, although
Although Dwayne the rock Johnson actually went to high school not too far from where I'm sitting. Did you know that?
That's true in Allentown
Bethlehem actually Bethlehem
I think you went to either
Either Liberty or Freedom High School, you know?
the way they need their high schools over there in Bethlehem. It's very confusing.
But he went to you to one of those two. His father, Rocky Johnson, was also a wrestler,
as was his grandfather, the high chief Peter Maivia. I did not know that.
The whole Allentown area was like a big hub of wrestling back in the old circuits.
Wow. Regional promotions. Wow. That's some thank you for, you know, you have to say,
when I say thank you for that you have to say what can I say except you're welcome.
I don't know if you're up on your modern kids films there, but now you know, and knowing
is half the bad.
Here he go.
Bring him back to the end.
All right.
Well, I'll give the quick answer to why it doesn't matter, right?
People will still stay tuned because we're going to talk about a bunch of other stuff.
The quick answer to why it doesn't matter is, right, it only matters if you think the
text itself has authority.
So then you have to come up with qualities of the text that give it authority.
Right.
Yeah, when it was written.
So anyway, we're gonna keep going now.
Exactly, exactly.
I should point out by the way, you know,
to have at least one Star Trek reference this half,
the rock actually appeared on an episode,
I think it was of, was it Voyager?
I think it appeared.
It was Voyager.
He battled Seven of Nine in a Sunkatsu area.
Yeah, yeah, he was sort of a gladiator
way out there in the Delta Quadrant.
so they had a sword that was a
type of falchion. Nice. So was used in student cuts. Nice. Nice. Alright. So I
doubled down on that reference. That's good. No, that's good. He does the eyebrow
thing in that too. You know that that that. Voyager was sort of the the flagship
show of UPN in the long ago time children. There was a United Paramount Network
that was an over there. They used to broadcast television over the air not
through a cable.
Anyway.
No.
through the interwebs.
And so Voyager was like the flagship show,
at the time, WWF, SmackDown, also on UPN.
So they did a lot of cross promotion.
There you go.
Wrestlers on Star Trek have Star Trek person show up
at a wrestling event.
It was kind of a golden age in some ways.
Yeah.
The idea was mostly lame.
Anyway.
It's true.
But they had a voyager, which is why everyone got it.
I don't know what to do.
reason I gave that quick answer was I was trying to help out our listeners who
hate it when we go on rambling digressions like I know I know I know I
said here here's a nugget but but but it's like you know it's like I feel like I
need to pop culture even harder you know when when when people are a little
impatient about that but yes okay so we talked about the the way that
religious texts especially the scriptures function in the ancient world and
and then how they arise and all that kind of stuff.
It's now, you know, move on the other side of the BCAD, right?
And we're gonna now start talking about cannons.
Cannon's description of a cannon.
Yeah, an actual list of books.
And what does that do?
What do you do with that, right?
So what is a cannon?
What does it even mean?
Yeah.
Why does that word come into play here, right?
So the word cannon to help us define it,
We're going to talk about first a couple of examples.
not related to scripture, right?
And then we'll come to scripture
because that'll become a little more clear what it means, right?
So we have this idea, especially the classical education
folks of the Western canon.
Yeah, right.
But there are these texts.
The books you should read as an English major.
Right, these are the texts that help shape our culture.
Right?
Yeah.
and
And by that I mean like Anglophone culture.
The whole restaurant civilization thing is kind of weird.
So like drawing a weird wavy line.
It's like that tool in paint
doesn't make like a circle.
It makes like the weird like blobby shape.
Right.
Like you kind of have to do that with history
to make Western civilization.
But there's this idea that once you've made that blobby shape,
right, you then say, well here are the books
please.
that you know, Plato's Republic, Shakespeare,
the Bible.
These are the only ones I can think of, right?
Freud.
Yeah.
Tommy, I don't think Freud, I don't,
I don't think he's of the Western kind of.
He is in the great books of the Western world, my friend.
Mortimer Adler would dare to disagree with you.
I'm fine with that.
So I can live my life without reading
Sigmund Freud are telling
anyone else to read, segment of Freud.
Yes.
I'm sure.
Anyway, so the Western literary canon, those kinds of great books, although great books
is probably a broader concept, but it's a similar concept.
Well, I mean, it's really a shortening of Mortar Radler's set, the great books of the
Western world.
So, whether people refer to great books program, that's usually actually what they're referring
to.
Okay.
So, but that kind of idea, right?
Or we use the term can.
in lots of nerd slash geek contexts.
Right?
So, there's this idea of, you know, Star Trek fans or Star Wars fans or Dr. Hoophant.
Well Dr. Hoophant don't argue about it because I mean, the idea of Dr. Hoophant is like
laughable on its face.
But we'll argue about what is canonical and what isn't.
Right.
Yeah, and it's interesting in Tolkien studies, mostly the conversation comes up just to
point out that there really is no
such thing that it's a useless category in Tolkien studies.
Right. Yeah. It's more argued against and even used by anybody in the fandom, honestly.
It's a bizarre idea because you're essentially arguing about what events are real in an imaginary
reality. Right. And which are unreal even in the imaginary reality.
Yeah. And the funny thing is, I mean, this is related, I mean, this is not just a nerd
geek thing they were talking about right
This is related to religious texts because like for instance, you know, one of the studies I'm making right now is I'm reading I'm reading Norse mythic texts and which actually there's not a huge number of them by the way.
The sources themselves is not a large amount of text, but there's variations between them.
And even as much as these might have been used in Norse religion in some way, we don't know in most cases.
You're going to say that this version is the, this is the true Odin, you know, or whatever,
or what about the fact that Loki seems to be relatively late?
I'm sorry, Marvel fans.
Loki is a relatively late addition probably to the Norse mythical, you know, source text.
There's variations.
So how do you say that this is the canon, the canonical version of the creation of the world
according to Norse mythology, right?
Thanks.
There's a lot of keys in Avengers number one. So clearly that's the canonical
True true can I argue with that Stanley and Jack Kirby men
Right and so so what we mean is
Tax that are considered in some way authoritative within that community
Right, text that bear some weight.
Right, you...
if we're talking about an imaginary reality, right? There are stories, like Star Trek 5,
where cybac is ridiculous, where just we all acknowledge that's not a thing.
I need my pain. And we ignore it. That's what you're saying.
And there are others that we exult in, right? I discuss, right? So even in that case, right?
It's the idea there's some kind of authority, there's some kind of weight, there's some kind of import to
them, right, that other text locks. These texts have shaped, right, with the Western canon,
right? The idea is that, right, whether you care for Shakespeare, whether you are able
to read and understand Shakespeare, like Shakespeare, the turns of phrase in Shakespeare, the dramatic
pivots in Shakespeare, these are things that have influenced the broader culture. Right,
time. So you go and see the North men and at some point you realize, hey man, this is Viking
hamlet what's going on right
But they have sort of been influential.
And so the important thing to draw out of this when we're talking about the canon of Scripture.
I mean obviously at the first layer, there's, yes, these are texts out of all the texts that have been handed down and copied and that we're aware of and that we might read.
These are the ones that have particular authority within our community.
that's like a second temple Jewish community
or whether that's a Christian community, right?
There are certain texts that have authority in our community.
The slightly deeper level of that,
the important thing to emphasize here
is that this is always descriptive and not prescriptive.
Right?
Yeah, so we're basically saying
this is how these texts have been used.
You know, it's for saying this is what occurred.
Not right.
not this is how they ought to be used.
But this is how they're used.
This text, right, if we're talking about scripture,
this text is read during the liturgy.
This text has been preached on and taught
and quoted in theological discussions for centuries.
This text, right, that has concretely happened in reality.
Yeah, right.
And so this is why sometimes, because occasionally,
we'll talk about, say, the Book of Enoch
or the Book of Jubilee's on this show,
Okay, so here we get...
ask, like, so are you saying that that book is canonical? And like, that's literally a
nonsensical question.
Right. Because it does not function as can in within the church,
right? You know, unless you're in the Ethiopian tradition.
Right. That's the only place where it does. Right. So like, it's literally,
it's not prescript, you can't like prescribe it. Right? Like if, if someone comes
out like VH1 used to in the good old days when VH1 should be
music. Like they would come out with a list of here's the hundred greatest rock songs of
all time, right? Or the hundred most influential bands of all time. And if like their top ten
bands were bands you'd never heard of, right? Like that wouldn't work. You wouldn't be
like, oh, well, I'd never heard of those bands, but those must be the greatest and most
influential bands of all time. You'd call it St. Anagins. Right. You'd be like, this is
What are you talking about?
Right. Right. How could you make this person under that person?
Yeah. Like the right way to do that would be by things like how often it gets played
or album sales or you know this kind of stuff that shows that is been used by this community
in this way. Right. But you would react to it. Not as you wouldn't even react to it as if it was
a prescription. You wouldn't say, Hey man, you can't show this lousy music down my throat.
You would react to it by saying, this is a bad description. Right. Right. Right. Right.
Why did you
rank this band above that band, right? Clearly that band is better than the other one, right?
That's a description, right? You're not describing reality correctly, right? So this kind
of candidate essentially is a description of reality. So you can't just eat it. But this
also means, this also means that there, there, there, there has never been in the orthodox
any...
any council, any emperor, any Illuminati group, any physical book of all,
a lot of monks, right, who went out and decreed these are the canonical books,
and they went on a rampage burning all the other ones.
Right, because I mean even when you do get canonical lists,
they are, as you said, descriptive. These are the books.
These are the ones that we've been reading.
And sometimes we're aware of these other ones.
They're okay, but they're not the same level as the first list, right?
Yeah, but more on that later.
Right, yeah.
It's not just like these are the only books
we've ever heard of in our lives, right?
Yeah, right.
So what are some examples of really early canons
in the history of Christianity?
So, well, we'll actually start before Christianity.
We'll start with this.
This is really something that emerges in Second Temple Judaism.
Before that, when you get into ancient Israel, right, this is where this stuff is coming together and being edited and forming, right?
Yeah, right.
So as these texts sort of emerge fully formed in second temple Judaism, right?
Then, and you have a variety of Jewish communities at that point.
You have Jewish communities that are still in Mesopotamia, you have Jewish communities in Egypt, you have Jewish communities in Palestine,
sign and then as the Greek and Roman periods go on they get scattered all over the known
world.
Jewish communities.
all over the place. And those individual communities are all functioning as
communities. They all have synagogues. In those synagogues, texts are being
being read in a ritual way. And so there are certain texts that are being read
and other texts that are not being read. And there's texts functioning in this way
and others that aren't. And this differs from community to community as they're
spread out. And so we can look at one example. One good example is the
community at Comoron, right at Wadi Comoron, which is from whence we get the Dead Sea Scrolls.
And they're a good example because we basically found their whole library.
They hid their library because the Romans were coming.
The Romans came, they didn't ever go back and retrieve it, right?
Convenient for us.
So we've now found it, right?
So we have a good idea of sort of all the text they had, all the text they were copying,
all the text they had preserved.
We can even get...
an idea of sort of the relative influence and authority of those texts in the community
based on how many copies there were.
Right.
So you got lots of copies that's way, you know, a lot of people can be reading it all at
once.
Right.
If you've got one old rady copy, probably not the most influential text, right?
In your community, right?
Because you haven't ever bothered to recopulate and preserve it.
Just like in my house, the book we have the most copies of is the Bible, but the second
after that, of course, is the Hobbit.
Yeah, just putting that out there.
And the third, oddly enough, is John Grisham's the firm.
I've never been to that brother Andrew.
I mean, why multiple copies?
It doesn't even make sense.
But, so if you go in order of copies at Kumaran,
the Dead Sea Scrolls, right, the number one book is Genesis.
Right number two is
the book of Enic, right? Number three is Exodus, yep. Number four is the book of Jubiles.
Okay. And in fact, if you add the copies of Enic and Jubiles together, there are more copies
of the two of them together than Genesis. So that is to say, Genesis isn't way ahead of the book of Enic.
It's a little ad. Yeah, right. So as we were saying, right.
these texts, it's not just, these are texts and scribes
are copying them and interpreting them
and debating their interpretation,
but these are functioning ritually.
This is why Enoch and Jubilee's are so important.
So the whole reason this community at Kumron existed
out in the desert by itself,
separate from the other communities
was over a dispute about the ritual calendar.
Well, wait, religious people argue out calendars.
Yes, they do, right?
And in this case, the founders of the community at Kumron
looked at the sagesese and said,
dare you use that Julian calendar, it is pagan. Literally, I mean, it's from this. You know, it's
named after a pagan emperor. It's a dirty pagan Roman calendar that Julian calendar. We want
nothing to do with you, right? And for them, even the Pharisees calendar, the Pharisees were too
liberal for that. Because the Pharisees calendar was using the old Israelite lunar calendar, but
a lunar calendar you have like 12, 30-day months.
So every couple of years you have to add like a whole month
like to line things back up, right?
Right, because the moon doesn't move like that.
Yeah, and yeah, the moon and the sun don't match well enough, right?
Right, that's what comes up.
So you have feast days bouncing around in the year, right?
And you have these things happening.
And the community of Kumeron looked at that and said,
clearly this is a man-made calendar.
This counter doesn't come from God, it comes from...
from humans because look how imperfect it is.
Right.
Look at what a mess it is.
You Pharisees and your traditions of men, right?
Right.
So for them, the whole basis of forming this community
was to observe and they observed sort of a strip town version
because they didn't have the actual temple
of the ritual life of ancient Israel,
sort of out in the desert.
But they observed it according to the ennotic calendar.
Hmm. Yeah. So why that one?
Well, this is officially the most boring part of the book of
Enic, right?
This is where people wash out.
If you try to read straight through the book of Enic, like that watch your
stuff, everybody's into that, right?
Then you roll into the second part, like the book of
similarities and stuff, and you get to the calendar stuff.
And it's like, right?
And people just stop reading.
But so the Adaka calendar that's laid out in great detail there is,
and the way it's laid out is Enic is taken by the angels and sees sort
all the movements of the heavenly host and all of this.
Right.
Plenitarium.
Yeah.
Kind of experience.
The calendar is revealed to him by God.
Right.
That this is the true divine calendar.
It's 364 days long.
But so in their minds though, that 364 day year, it's mathematically perfect.
you have three thirty day months then you have an interstitial day.
three more 30-day months interstitial day.
And when you do it that way,
the feasts are on the same day every year, right?
It all lines up.
It's very regular.
I have to point out.
Yeah, I have to point out
this is also basically the Shire calendar.
It's 30-day months with an occasional extra day in between.
So I don't know, there's a paper
to be written about the relationship
between the Inakik calendar and the calendar of Hobbits.
Just put that out there.
Bilbo
and you know, yeah, totally. And so, but this is, I mean, this is a very common idea in the
ancient world that mathematical perfection is somehow divine. Yes, right. Pythagoras play. Yes, right.
Yeah. The Pythagorean theorem is a cultic theorem. So, again, the reason this book is so important
to them is not just that they got excited when people talked about giants, right, though they may
well have because they also had the book of the Giants.
But because this is the whole basis of their ritual life, is this calendar from this text.
Right? So it's also worth noting that in addition to a lot of attention is paid to the
biblical texts that were found at Comeron and the Densy Scrolls, but there's also a whole bunch of sectarian texts, meaning
Text that are only found there and text that are specific to them.
Like this is how, and it's their economy for the community.
community. It's their community rules, right? Yeah. And things. Here's how we govern ourselves. Here's how we resolve disputes. Here's who's in charge. Here's how they get to be in charge, right?
The bylaws. Right. Right. Right. Or a monastic rule. Right. That kind of idea. Right. But again, it's that economy idea that we already saw, right, functioning in Scripture. So their cannon is this set of tax that's clearly a great variance with, for example, the Pharisees and the Sadducees.
Yes, sir and
deliberately so to some level.
Right.
So what we see when we look at all these different communities,
second-table Jewish communities spread out all over the world,
we could say certain things in terms of trends,
right?
It's sort of generalizations, right?
So everybody has the Torah,
right?
Somewhere in there.
And we should mention that these communities
all would regard each other as Judeans.
Jews. Well, you know, yeah, okay, roughly. But they didn't consider the sadducees to be okay. That's true. That's true. All right. But nonetheless, they are all saying, you know, they all believe themselves to be truly Jews. Right.
In some cases, yeah. And in some cases, there's some level of mutual recognition, even if there's arguments. And yet, they don't all share the same canon of Scripture.
remotely. Right, yeah, right. So the
Everybody's got the Torah somewhere in there.
Now, somewhat surprisingly to people,
there are significant second-table Jewish communities
that are not really considered to be forms
of Torah-based Judaism.
The idea of non-Toura-based Judaism confuses some people,
right, because of how it's been drilled into our head,
and because we're thinking of rabbinic Judaism.
And it's true that for the most second-table Jewish communities,
The Torah was the most...
important, right, text, but not all of them, right, but even
those where it was not at the top, right, if it was the
basic kind of it was still in there, right, they didn't
reject the Torah, right, even the Samaritans had their own
version of the Pentateuch. It was tinkered with, but the
Samaritan Pentateuch was a thing, right. So then when you get
into the Neveim, right, the prophets, those are mostly the
Have you seen this, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry...
You're going to find most, if you include Daniel with the prophets instead of the writings
right, and if you include Jeremiah you've got different versions of the book of Jeremiah
right, but for the most part those books are going to be the same.
But then as we mentioned with the writings, the Ketuvian, there's big Ketchall in the Hebrew
Bible in the Old Testament, that's where you've got stuff all over the map.
So Ethiopian Jewish communities have Jubilee's and Ena.
a whole bunch of stuff, right, that most Palestinian Jewish communities don't have that aren't
functioning that way there. And then you've got Jewish communities in what's now spain in Rome.
Right. And so, which of the writings could even in Palestine, where, you know, obviously
Judea is, where you'd think they'd have this sort of more nailed down. They were arguments
about the writings, whether Ecclesiastes was or wasn't authoritative.
whether Esther was or wasn't authoritative, whether Ben Sirak was or wasn't authoritative.
So there are these disagreements even there, right?
Sort of in the hub, right?
And then making it even more confusing, right?
There isn't like, because again, they don't have like a Bible.
They don't have like one book with all these texts in it.
Scrolls.
A bunch of scrolls.
Yeah.
It scrolls.
and
You know a given synagogue might fully acknowledge the authority of
Samuel and kings, but just not have a scroll
It's so not ever actually read it
Use it. Yeah, their public worship right they're not rejecting it. They just don't have it right and you've also got these sort of dotted lines at the borders
Where you'll have someone like if we're gonna talk more about Josephus a little bit but Josephus who's a Pharisee
does not accept
Jubilee's as
being canonical as being an authoritative work, but when you read his Jewish
antiquities and he's going through the history of, especially the early history of the world
up through the time of Moses, he cribs all this stuff from the book of Jubiles.
Yeah, right. So that's kind of proving or demonstrating, I should say, that just because you treat a book
as in some level authoritative doesn't mean that you're saying it's part of the canon of scripture.
Because whether it's authoritative in his community as a Pharisee is an ab-
objective thing.
So he may like the book of Jubilee.
He may find it fascinating.
He may think it gives lots of important traditions.
He may think it's reliable.
But there's no question whether it's canonical or not.
It wasn't because he was a Pharisee.
It's descriptive.
But so each of these communities
has its own functional canon.
They're listed descriptively.
There's no committee like voting on books
any of these communities.
And when the gospel comes to these various Jewish communities,
they just inherit whatever that canon is as their Old Testament.
Yeah, they just keep using it.
And so this is how the canon of the Ethiopian Jews
becomes the canon of the Ethiopian church.
This is how the canon of Alexandria and Judaism
becomes the old
of the church in Alexandria, right?
And so this, and this is why as we talked about in our episode about how to read the Bible,
this is why to this day Eastern churches have different Old Testament canons functionally,
because we just inherited them.
Together with no vote, there was no like weeding through them.
And it's okay.
It's okay, everybody.
We don't need to.
Okay, this is your Jewish Bible.
is our Old Testament, right?
That was it, right?
And then added to it, right?
So this brings up the question
of what would become the Hebrew Bible, right?
The rabbinic canon, right?
There's a little bit of an urban legend here, right?
You will hear people talk about the Council of Jomnia,
right?
Which is not a thing.
Whenever you hear somebody talk about non-Christians
having a church council?
your eyebrow should go up. The aforementioned rock the Dwayne Johnson.
Rock the Dwayne. That's better than Dwayne the Rock.
So, right, you should get a little suspicious, right? That maybe somebody, like we said before,
they're a Christian, so they're looking at Judaism from a Christian perspective, right?
So what that's about,
Jomnia is where the-
major like rabbinical school of the Pharisees was after the construction of Jerusalem by the Romans.
I mean what does it actually have to do with this question?
Well it became sort of the teaching hub for nascent rabbinical Judaism.
Okay.
So in a sense, in a sense, everything about rabbinic Judaism sort of has its origins from
Jamnia right like um but that does
doesn't mean that the rabbis got together and voted on what books would be in the Hebrew
Bible.
Right.
The key thing here.
Yeah.
It's just this is these are the books that were functioning as canonical within that community.
For the Pharisees.
Right.
It's the Pharisee of Canon, right?
And that was the Canon of the Pharisees before any of this.
Right.
This is what Josephus says is the Canon.
These are the books that were authoritative for Josephus because Josephus was a Pharisee.
So this is the...
the 39 books that are now the Old Testament in most Protestant Bibles. When you see the Church
Fathers and rabbinical sources refer to them, they usually refer ancient ones. They usually
refer to them as the 22 books. That's because a bunch of them were combined on the same scroll. So like
what we call the minor prophets, the 12 of them were on one scroll, the book of the 12.
Right? Yeah. So that just weeds out like 11 books. Right.
as we said, judges and Ruth, first and second,
Samuel R.I.s scroll, et cetera, et cetera.
I mean, the funny thing is is that even if we talk about 66
or whatever number of books of the Bible,
we tend to call it the Bible, which simply means the book.
And that's because we've combined it
into a single codex that you can just have them all together
as a book.
It's a library, really, right?
Right.
So part of the reason why the John
stuff gets started. Part of the reason why people want to say, well, no, that Hebrew Bible
canon that emerges in rabbinic Judaism, that was the fair say canon. That was just everybody
in the first century accepted that those were the canonical books. We sometimes hear this
from our Protestant friends when arguments break out over, you know, for example, the longer
Let him kill you.
and or the longer Greek canon or write any of this,
in terms of specific Old Testament books,
say, no, everybody knew at the time.
And when they say that, they're essentially taking a quote
from Josephus, the aforementioned Josephus.
Yes, who stands in for everybody.
Right, Josephus makes a modest claim,
modest in the Jonathan Swift sense of the term
about canonism.
Yeah, okay, so we're gonna read this to you.
And I'll just note at the outset here
that there's a few ellipses in here,
so we're skipping some bits.
Yes, because it would go on very long.
Right, but it escalates quickly.
So here we go.
Okay, here we go.
Therefore, it naturally even necessarily follows
that we do not possess a myriad of divergent books
which conflict with each other.
Our books, those which are rightly recognized
are only 22 and contain the record of all time.
Of these five are the books of Moses made up of the laws and the traditional history
from the beginning of humanity to the death of the law giver.
From the death of Moses until Arctic Circuses, who succeeded Circuses as King of Persia,
the prophets who followed Moses wrote the history of the events of their own times in 13
books.
The remaining four books contain hymns to God and rules for the conduct of human life.
From Arctic Circuses to our own day, the complete history has been written, but has not been
deemed worthy of equal credit with the earlier records.
because of the failure of the succession of the prophets. Although long ages have now passed,
no one has dared either to add, to remove or to alter a syllable. It is instinctual for every
Judean from the day of his birth to recognize them as the proclamation of God, to obey them,
and if need be willingly to die for them." And that's from the Contra Apeon chapter 1,
37 through 44.
Look, that's pretty amazing that
that'd be saying
And Ian Babies are born, born recognizing his canon.
Well, first of all, I have to ask, why did you not name any of your son's Arta Andrew?
It's an interesting question.
It's an honor.
It's an opportunity.
But Anderson would be the equivalent, right?
Just call him Anderson.
No, that's suspicious.
I mean, just call him Arty.
I mean, it's fine, Nick.
So yeah, so we have, we have,
claims here at the end. So a lot of this seems fairly reasonable and you can see why some will
be followed. Those other books you're talking about, Roman Catholics and Orthodox folks,
yeah they're there but they're not on the same level because the succession of prophets failed.
So you got something there. But here's the problem. This argument is all leading up to where it goes.
right which is Josephus making the following claims. First of all, long eight
have passed since these books were written but no one has dared to add, remove, or alter,
a syllable. Right. Just that's not not reality. Not true. Just not true. Right. Right. So that's
not true. Then it's instinctual for every Judean. Right. It's like built into someone by virtue of
the beast Jewish. Right. You're born with the you're born with the Canon. From the day of your birth.
Right? So the baby comes out from its-
mother's womb, recognize the authority of these 22 books and no others. Recognize that
specifically is the proclamation of God. They all every Judean obeys every word of them
their entire life. Like Josephus have you read them. And not only do they abandon every
single one of them is willing to die for them. Every single one.
slight exaggeration. There might be some hyperbole there. Right. Right. Right. This might be
a Pharisee talking to Romans and presenting his form and his understanding of Judaism as the real
Judaism. Right. Because, you know, what are Romans know about the differences in canonical
collections between here's community right over against these other
other set.
right. So that might be going on there. And so I think
basing arguments about the Old Testament canon on taking this kind of
hyperbole from somebody like Josephus who remember is not a Christian.
Right. Taking this very literally giving Josephus this authority, right, which is
authority that most of the people who use this quote authority.
would not give to any of the church fathers who were actually Christians, for example, who were outside the Bible.
That doesn't seem to me to be a good platform to stand on to make an argument.
So we've seen, and we've talked about all these people out there who very much disagreed with Josephus on this,
this on this, because they were aware of reality.
So what we see when we turn to the New Testament canon,
So the Old Testament canon, the idea of these books being authoritative is inherited, right, from the
second temple Jewish communities from which the Christian communities emerge.
The New Testament canon forms organically in the same way that the Old Testament canon did.
Yeah, meaning nobody ever sat down and picked.
Right.
They didn't know one ever, ever Dan Brown.
Never, not constantine, not theodosias, not, you know, anybody, no tribunals, no nobody,
sat down and said, okay, well, we've got these 12 gospels.
Let's vote on each one.
Okay, these four past, these other eight, burn them, right?
Yeah, I mean, and there's even, you can even hear sometimes Orthodox people will say,
You know where the cannon was decided at NICIA and I'm like so so
We have multiple accounts of the proceedings at NICIA.
None of them say anything about the canon.
The closest you could get, I'm going to try and be as generous as I can.
The closest you get to that is that we have from one source that afterwards,
state-constituting commissioned 50 Bibles containing the old and new testaments to be written.
new testaments to be written. I mean, okay.
But there's no idea the context.
Yeah, yeah, there's just bibles.
No idea the context.
Hypothetically, you could say, well,
that was the canonical one.
I guess we don't know what in it, right?
Right.
Yeah.
So yeah, the dog don't hunt.
And also, maybe more surprisingly to people,
they didn't sit around arguing about it much.
right here
Again, it was descriptive, not prescriptive.
Right, because so, you know, it would just be questions of fact,
not questions of, you know, authoritative opinion about stuff.
Like, you know, you read the early church fathers.
I don't remember, I mean, I've read most of the texts
of the first couple of centuries.
I don't remember coming across any debates like that.
Right, nobody's saying like, man,
you people need to start reading second Peter.
Right.
Yeah, it's like being pushed. Yeah, right exactly. It's just like well, this is what's used in our church. Yeah
so
So yeah, there's not these these these these big debates in fact
Right most of these things are settled very early right so by the time you get to AD 150
All across the world and the churches at least in all of the major cities
They're using the four gospels that were used.
using today. Yeah, and they're and they're in one collection together, right? Like a single scroll or I don't know
they were well, I don't remember what coding codices. Yeah, I was just saying I don't remember when when codices start being used, but yeah,
the Christians who start doing it really. So, uh, and it's the four gospels together. It's not like one community is using
Matthew and another one's using Luke and it's like, you know, peanut butter and chocolate we get together and now we're
We're gonna use both, right?
Now we met this other guy who has to...
gospel of St John. Yeah, so there's this sense that there's this sense that these four books go
together and everyone you know that we are all using them together. Yeah. And that's despite
the fact that they differ in some details, right? And people noticed because they were reading them.
It didn't bother them. But we'll leave that for now. But those four and pretty much all those four.
And the earliest of the gospels that modern people want to act like maybe had a chance.
of being in the Bible, which would be like the gospel of Thomas, right?
Pretty much the earliest one. That was being written around that time.
Right. So by the time that was being written, it was already settled.
And so Sanior and AS could say, Hey man, you got this, this gospel and that
master gospel is like, every church of the world uses these four and only these four.
You know that. I know that.
Where are you coming from with this stuff?
Yeah. And so like this, this idea that there is this big conspiracy to weed out
all the
these are their gospels. It's just again, as you say, it is a dog that does not hunt.
Yes. And so Paul's epistles were collected together even earlier, right, by 80-100. They
were circulating together as a group. Right.
Second Peter refers to them as a group. Yeah. I mean, this is just within a few years
after the death of the Apostle John, right? I mean, yeah. Yeah. And every, every manuscript
that's come down to us is a copy of the collection. We do not have a single copy of
you
individual letter of Saint Paul.
Circulate together.
And this includes Hebrews.
The earliest one we have from the mid-second century,
it's called P46, P is for Papyrus,
because that's what it's on, and 46,
because it's the 46th one we found.
That includes Hebrews, and Hebrews is right after Romans,
because they're arranged in order of length.
Yeah, and we should point out, by the way,
that just because we have, when we use,
you know, the dating is, it's by this date.
And when we say bye.
you know, AD 100. We mean that's the earliest known example of that, not, and this is the
date of publication. Right. In that exact year, they collected them. Right. It's to that date.
Yeah. That's the oldest point we can give that, you know, that we know of. Right. And so, so that's why
for the record, even though we have church fathers saying, you know, I read Hebrews, I'm not sure
St. Paul Road Hebrews, right?
I can't even look like another.
You know, we have that.
It's always St. Paul's epistle to the Hebrews.
Why?
Because it's in the collection of St. Paul's epistles.
Yeah.
Right?
So that's why it's always when it comes down to it,
it's St. Paul's epistles to the epistle to the Hebrews,
regardless of what other conjecture there is or thought there is.
So then in terms of the other stuff,
the other stuff of the New Testament,
which is generally the general epistles
and revelation and revelation is a special case
that we'll get to in a minute.
Yeah.
The general epistles we know are circulating as a collection at least by 180
And this is basically what you know in most Bible's these days these days would be James through Jude right right?
Yeah, yeah right and and we know that they were circulating as a collection by then because
Clement of Alexandria writes a commentary on them as a collection
hmm
around that time so that's why we know
But sometime before that, they were collected together.
And those texts are the ones where we see the big variations
in different Christian communities.
So there are some communities that very clearly only knew
about First Peter and weren't aware of Second Peter.
Right.
And there were other communities that had both.
There were a lot of communities that didn't have Jude.
There are...
or Jude is actually kind of interesting
because this weird thing happens
before the, during the centuries
before the Council of Nicaea,
where at first there are all these communities
that had never seen the epistle of Jude.
And so we see people who are aware of the epistle of Jude
saying, no, this is a really good canonical letter,
even though it's really short.
This is a really good canonical letter
because see, look, it quotes the book of Enoch.
Huh.
Right?
And so then as things shift
in terms of people's impression of the book of Enoch,
Right.
and the authority comes to hold or not hold in most Christian communities, then all of
us on the people who still kind of like the Book of Enoch are like, yeah, but St. Jude quotes
it.
So, St. Jude by that time becomes more firmly established, right, in terms of all the churches.
And so they start using it to argue for the Book of Enoch instead of vice versa.
But so there's, that's where you get the most distinctions, right?
even in those cases.
because it's not that like places where rejecting those books.
It's not like, we're fully aware of the epistle of St. James
and we don't cotton to it, right?
We've got a way from Martin Luther for that.
It's just communities didn't know about it, right?
And so the way this sort of organically happens, the way there comes to be sort of one
canon across Christian communities is that Christian communities, as they live their communal
life and as they develop.
They encounter other Christian communities, or at least other communities who identify themselves as Christian communities.
And when they do, there's sort of this process of mutual recognition that goes on.
And for all the Martin Boober fans out there, he talks about the other and the other self.
The idea being other when you identify something as other you're saying this is not me and not like me
Whereas when you identify someone as an other self, you're saying this is another person, but they are a person like me
Right, and so there's sort of this is this community a community another community like ours
Or is this community something different is this a different type of
community, right?
and so one of the things that goes into that right there
They're all better factors that go into that they're liturgical life right the way they worship the way they pray
how they do all these things are factoring into it.
But one of those is what texts they read from authoritatively.
Right?
And what we find is that when these communities come into contact with each other,
if they're using the same four Gospels and they're using St. Paul's Epistles,
and they're like, well, these guys have two Epistles of St. Peter, they say,
and we only have this one.
They don't say, begun heretic.
Right?
Filthy apostates get out.
right? They say, no, this is another community like us, right? They just have this other
epistle of St. Peter that we don't have. And hey, let's take a look at it. It's kind
of interesting, right? Whereas, when they encounter another group and like they're doing
the Eucharist differently and they're celebrating different feasts and they're talking about
the Ogdo ad and they're reading the Gospel of truth. Not the four Gospels, they go, yeah,
sir, this is a Wendy's, right? They're like, this is something, this is a church,
is chicken is a church, right? This is not right. This is not one of us, right? Yeah.
And so over time, right, and this is still really how the Orthodox Church is
structured to this day. The Orthodox Church is a communion of local churches
who recognize each other and are in communion with each other. As Orthodox, and so
that develops and as that develops this 26 book canon of the New Testament
develop the emerges right you may have no
26 and 9.
26.
Yeah, exactly.
Because that brings us to the revelation of St. John.
Yeah, which is a special case.
Yes, it has a fascinating history.
And if you want to know all about it, let me tell you, ancient faith ministries own,
Dr. Jeannie Constantino, her doctoral dissertation was published under the title, Guiding to
to a blessed.
end and is about the reception history of the book of Revelation in the East, especially
centering on St. Andrew of Cessery's commentary on the book of Revelation.
And her doctoral dissertation is literally a magisterial on this topic.
So if you can find it.
Yeah, it's about not the A-team.
The dissertation if you could find it.
That's about $75 and for a hard-
cover on Amazon right now. I just checked if you could get it through
interlibrary loan. If you could, if you could, if you could, if you could
track it that right, it is the place to go on this. But yeah, right, we're
going to give sort of brief summary, which I'm sure if she ever
listens to this, she will thoroughly critique, right, because it's going to
lack nuance, because we're going to do it in brief. And I might even get
some details wrong. But so in the broad strokes, right, the reception
history.
relationship is really interesting because, uh,
Revelation of St. John has this very early attestation to it being
this authoritative text, right? So St. Justin, the philosopher or
St. Justin martyr, St. Irenaeus of Leone, these, these early fathers
who, who studied in the area around Ephesus, right, who studied
in the areas around Pontus, right?
Where St. John had it...
ministry. So, there are an ASS, a spiritual grandson of St. John. They all attest, I mean,
St. John, here in ASS gives us the exact date that St. John had his vision, ADV-5. Wow.
Right. Like, we don't have that kind of information about any other book of the New Testament. No.
There's a super early attestation as to who wrote it when, where, right, the whole thing, right?
Yeah, um, so you would think, well, hey, this should be right in
there with the four Gospels and St. Paul's epistles, right? Well, no. Because what happens
is the teaching of kiliasum emerges. Yeah, which which just to summarize in case you haven't
heard that word before is the the idea that there is going to be a literal thousand year
age of the church. I don't know there's variations on the beginning and end of that, right?
but that's kind of the middle of Christ on earth.
Yeah, Kingdom of Christ on Earth is going to be exactly a thousand years long.
And, you know, might be in the future, might be now.
But there's no reason to.
Kileism is in the future.
Okay. Yeah.
Yeah.
What separates Kileism from like modern forms of pre-millennialism, right?
Dispensational and otherwise is that they're not because they're not the same thing.
Kileism wasn't based on in the way dispensational pre-millennialism is.
It wasn't based on...
covenantal theory, right? Like, it's an old covenant, new covenant. It wasn't
particularly based on, there's no connection to ethnic Judaism. It was, and that
thousand year period that Messianic age in the future, meaning the Messianic
age isn't now, was one of like earthly delights. Right. Right. Everybody has all
the food, everybody has all the folks and all the fun.
So that was kiliasum and while sort of forms of that were tolerated, even they're even
a handful of church fathers, I think Cedar and Aes is more debatable on this than some
folks do.
May have held to some version of this, right?
It was sort of tolerated versions of it were sort of tolerated with people who were otherwise
orthodox. But it was
was picked up as an element of certain other
heresies. Yeah, right. It gets associated with with
mountainism in particular, right? Right. And so for people who
don't know a lot about mountainism, Montana's was this fellow
who proclaimed himself to be the the parakeet promised by
Jesus. The the comforter. Yeah. So he said he was the one who
Jesus said was coming that he was a prophet. He traveled around
with tube.
Propheticis
They I'm sure it was platonic and
Must have been yes and
And they also were prophetesses and
They did a lot of glossololia and stuff and so all that's really problematic and they were also kill yes
Right yeah, and so not only were they kill yes, but
My monotidism was...
often referred to as the Pontic Heresy because it emerged from that same region.
Yeah.
Right.
And a lot of the Kilias would cite Revelation to support their view.
The Revelation of St. John.
Right.
So it kind of gets a bad rap because of its association with this.
This very live Heresy.
I mean, it wasn't just one guy, some wacko wandering the countryside.
I'm here as a
It was a fairly big movement.
I mean, it pulled in Tertolian.
Yeah.
So, this was a major heresy, right?
And remember, this is not that,
well, all these books that all these churches had been using
the book of Revelation, and then they found,
oh, wait, the mountainous quote this?
Well, burn it.
Right?
No, no.
Because lots of heretics quoted lots of books of the Bible.
Right, that didn't cost me.
you can't read the books of the Bible because they heretic quoted them. But it's that it wasn't in
widespread use. Yeah, it was mostly at local to Asia Minor, aka Sir, Sir, there is. Yeah, and people
who are from there. So when this is a book that your community is unfamiliar with, and in your early
encounters with it, a heretic is quoting it. It's a little sus. Right? So it kind of
got tired with that same brush. So it takes a few centuries for the book of
Revelation to really get rehabilitated and sort of re-accepted. And that
happens through the work of a couple of saints, right? So Saint Jerome in the
West, in the fifth century, Andrew Cessaria in the East, in the sixth century,
both do the same thing separately.
They both take in each of them
takes a different one because Jerome's is in Latin and St. Andrew's is in in Greek.
They take a commentary on Revelation written by a Kiliast and they revise it.
They didn't have plagiarism rules back then.
They were no intellectual property laws.
They took it, they revised it and took the Kiliasm out.
Yeah.
Right.
They looked at it and they said, you know, this is a pretty solid commentary on this text.
If it weren't for all this Kiliasm nonsense, right?
they took it out and they published
under their own name. And so now in the West, oh, St. Jerome's commentary on the revelation of St.
John. Right. Right. Let's read this. Right. And so through the commentary, they said,
oh, there's another way of reading this text that doesn't lead to all these these
theoretical wacky ideas. Right. And the same thing happens in the East. We say,
in our accessories commentary.
And become so influential, if you get like...
You can buy now Archbishop of Verkis commentary on revelation
Okay, and if you get it and read it
It's a commentary on St Andrew's commentary on revelation
So it's that foundational yeah, it's just like here's what St Andrew says right and here's now I would apply that
Yeah, so if I remember correctly what what Dr. Jeanne
Demonstrates is that
For the or for the east you know
you know, um,
Revelation becomes canonical, not just by means of this commentary put forth by St.
Andrew of Cicilia, but it becomes canonical almost accompanied by that commentary in the
sense that his reading of it was an authoritative reading.
Right.
It comes with an interpretation essentially, which is one of the several ways in which this
particular story is different from the other books.
It's not Revelation is read by the Kilias.
It's Revelation is read by Andrew Cesaria.
And if I remember correctly, then the timing,
so you know, St. Jerome is doing this about a century before St. Andrew Cesaria.
And so it kind of happens early enough in the West that it becomes part of the electionary.
It happened quicker in the West too.
Yeah. It happened more quickly in the West.
And, and, and late enough in the East that it doesn't really get into the election.
Yes, and I know folks, folks, save the emails so Father Andrew doesn't have to read them. I won't anyway
We know that there are individual instances there are places at the monastery at Patmas in
Alexandria and and in certain menacing services where
Someone physically in a church is reading the book of Revelation
We mean it's not part of the regular cycle of readings. Yeah, if you go and pick up an epistle book
in my
So, the most Orthodox Church is, they're not readings from the book of Revelation in the
cycle.
It's all the other books except for the Gospels in Revelation and the Gospel book, also
logically.
It does not contain Revelation.
That's what we're talking about.
And it's not because the book of Revelation is not canonical in the Orthodox Church, it's
just because of the historical road it took to coming to, to all this authority.
even we're going to talk more about
St. Nicholas in our third half, but even in the ninth century
St. Nicholas tells us that there are still some churches who
Didn't recognize at that late date in the past that didn't recognize the book of Revelation yet
Wow, so this really took a long time, but it did happen after all that time. Yeah, exactly. All right
Well all that said we're gonna go to our second and final break and we will be right back in a moment
and
Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
New from Ancient Faith Publishing.
welcoming gifts, sacrifice in the Bible and Christian life by Jeremy Davis.
find surprising answers in this book. You'll learn that sacrifice had a very different
significance for ancient people than it does for us today. You'll hear how it drifted away
from this ancient significance into a fundamentally different meaning in our modern world. You'll
discover how old testament sacrifices were gifts from the heart only tangentially related to killing
and death. You'll see in Christ's cross the ultimate gift that I-
us into communion with God, and you'll find inspiration to offer your own gifts alongside
Christ, inviting God into your life.
welcoming gifts, sacrifice in the Bible and Christian life.
Now available in paperback, ebook and audiobook at store.inchantfaith.com
Yeah, there's that crunchy metal theme.
Thanks a lot once again for that Rob.
We appreciate it.
So I know everybody likes that one.
great. So people should buy that book of Father Jeremy's. Yeah. Have I mentioned that? Yeah.
Like if you have money such that you can purchase a book that would be the book to purchase.
Exactly. Exactly. Yeah. There you go. Everybody get that book in between reading our books.
So all right, we'll welcome back. I'm going to go as far as to say. Just go ahead and get that book.
Don't worry about order.
Don't worry about the stack of books you already have that you haven't read.
Wow. Yes, it will stand up and testify against you at the judgment.
But still pop it to the top.
Go and get this book. Nice. Yeah.
There you go. We endorse it.
All right. Well, look back as the third half of the Lord of Spirits.
We're talking about texts and how they function canonically.
What exactly that means?
How they're used authoritatively within the Orthodox church.
And we just wrapped up talking about
especially the New Testament, particularly the revelation of St. John.
And now in the third half, we're going to talk about some other books that occasionally people say wacky things like,
why do you guys act like the Book of Yenak is canonical?
And we have to roll our eyebrows and say,
we have never actually acted like that.
Because...
How does one roll an eyebrow?
I'm still stuck on doing...
You're still thinking about Duane.
It's true.
F***!
Well, you said you said rock the Dwayne Johnson earlier. So I think we're both a little punch
you know, rock the Dwayne. It's Dwayne the rock. Yeah, roll the eyebrow, raise an eyebrow.
It's when you roll your eye and eyeballs and raise your eyebrows at the same time. That's
what that action is like what other Dwayne is there such that you would say he is not
The Dwayne.
Wow.
The Dwayne?
No.
Come on.
All right.
So yes, there are other texts that we read as Orthodox Christians, that we treat as
authoritative, but that we don't treat as canonical, right?
This is a thing.
It's okay, everybody.
That aren't read aloud in the church.
That don't form the liturgical ritual function.
Right.
traditional the traditional word for these books, especially the the first.
First set of those is apocrypha.
That's the word.
You can talk about what that means.
Yeah.
So, and again,
there's a caveat to carry over here.
We're being descriptive, right, of reality.
So even when we talk about these other texts, right?
When we're trying to figure this out,
we're not working off of some preconceived theological notion,
Right, and then...
and working that out.
This is, we're describing what has in reality historically
happened and happens today.
How these texts function today and how they have
functioned in the past.
It's descriptive.
OK.
Right.
So we've talked before about, and I know we have.
See, I say the same things, and I say them over and over again.
So sometimes I forget what I've said on this show
and what I've said somewhere else.
It's alright.
Like to myself in the bathroom or people
But the bathroom commentaries the bathroom commentaries by father Stephen D.Un
What's amazing when I walk around talking to myself my wife will tell you this is I start making hand gestures like I
Engage in in self rhetoric
Wow is probably sinful in some way
But so
But I know for sure because we've gotten questions from listeners.
We've talked to...
So this show about that there are in the east
and the understanding of candidacity and authority
that there are these three categories.
That it's not just a binary thing of one or zero.
Right?
Yeah.
This text is completely authoritative
and inerrant and infallible.
And this other text is not that
and so throw it away.
Right?
So it's the same level as Moby Dick.
Like it's irrelevant.
Right?
I don't know why keep going to Moby Dick either.
I don't know, yeah.
Gulliver's Travels.
They miss a gob.
I'm not to Jonathan Swift, man.
I mean, these loops, recursive loops.
Count of Monte Cristo.
OK.
Yeah, we haven't had Dumas yet.
So there's those texts that are read in the church,
those that are read in the home and those that
are not to be read.
Right?
So you'll get the folks, right?
We all went to high school with these people, right?
They had to write a paper on something, right?
They said, right, a paper on World Peace.
And they'd get up and start with Webster's Dictionary
to find the World Peace, is, right?
So when it comes to talking about apocrypha,
someone will get up and say, the word apocrypha
means hidden or secret.
Right, these are the dark essences.
the ancient church. Dan Brown again rears his ugly head. Renowned author Dan Brown.
So the idea that these are some of them mysterious or that they were banned from the Bible and
someone hid them somewhere. That's not really what I mean. Yes, that is what the word
where we can mean hidden or secret,
but it could also just mean private,
yeah, in the private public.
Right.
meaning you don't read it in the church, you read it at home, right?
Private reading.
It's just like, for instance, that there's lines in the liturgy where the rubric, if you're
reading it in Greek, it says that the priest reads a certain prayer, you know, mysticos,
mystically.
But that just means relatively quietly.
See, I was making the gestures again.
Oh, I've been messing up.
Mystic gestures.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
Yeah, but I'll talk to you.
strange. So, right. And so if you want like an exhibit A, right, of the type of thing
in this middle category of books read in private or books read in the home, right?
Exhibit A of that is the shepherd of Hermes, which you usually find collected with the
apostolic fathers, right? Even though it's kind of a weird genre, it's kind of a prophetic
book from the sunset.
right, AD. But so the Meritorian Canon was called the Meritorian Canon because it's
the earliest list we have of which books of the Bible were authoritative in
someone's community. We're not sure exactly who, whoever wrote it, right?
Refers to the Shepherd of Hermas, and it says that the Shepherd of Hermas ought to be
red but not
in the church because the number of the prophets is complete and it is after the Apostles.
So he says, you ought to read this but we don't read it in the church, we don't read it in the
gathering publicly because the Old Testament is complete and this was written after the time of
of the apostles, so it's sort of not eligible to be New Testament, right? In our term.
They weren't calling it the Old Testament,
the New Testament at the time.
Yeah, it's notable that it doesn't say,
it's not read in church,
and no one should read it ever anywhere.
Actually, it says it ought to be read.
Yes, it positively should be read by people.
Right.
But we don't read it in the church,
because it doesn't belong to either of these two categories
of books that we do read in the church.
Right, right.
So...
There's an example of one of those books, and there's an example of someone in the third quarter of the Second Century,
in the middle part of the Second Century, who is thinking of texts in that way, that there are these texts in this middle category.
And part of what engenders this is the fact that so historically we see when we talk about
second temple Judaism and second temple Jewish literature.
During that post-exotic period, there's this explosion of writing activity in all of these Jewish communities.
So you end up with these communities producing their own sectarian texts,
and having different texts are different places, and different texts being compiled in different ways.
So you get different versions of the same book. So there's all of this literary activity.
And then in the second century, not at the Council of John Neha,
is is nascent rabbinic duty
is being formed, part of what they think went wrong. So they're looking at Christianity
and they're like, from their perspective, in Nathan rabbinic Judaism, they're like,
wow, this all went really badly, right? Because from their perspective, Christians are
a heretical Jewish sect at this point, right? Right. Right. It was just been expelled from the synagogue.
So they say one of the places where we went wrong was all of this literature. Right.
There was this uncontrolled production of...
literature and thoughts and ideas and religious ritual practice and all of this it all got
out of hand and look what happened right and so there's actually a ban on writing yeah and what
that concretely means because again it's not like rabbis were writing around on horses burning
books either. What that concretely meant is that at the big rabbinical schools...
like John Nia at the major of Binnacle Schools, they didn't do any writing. They didn't write
down. They didn't preserve traditions in writing. They did it orally. All the teaching was done
orally. The learning was done orally. Traditions were handed down from generation to generation, just
orally. And it's not until you get into like the fifth century that the track dates of the Talmud
start being formed. Right. Yeah. And ban on writing, sorry, gets lifted. And that's why it's in the
the Talmud.
that you start getting, saying is attributed to like first century AD rabbis written down
for the first time.
Right.
So, that happens within the non-Christian Jewish communities that survive, which is mainly
fairsake Judaism that becomes rabbinic Judaism.
Yeah, because the rest kind of don't continue.
Yeah, for various reasons.
Right.
I mean, the Sadducees, their whole power base was the temple, no temple, no Sadducees,
right?
They become unimportant.
But Christians keep writing.
Yeah, this activity continues in Christianity.
So it's not just the New Testament documents.
There's other books alongside the New Testament documents.
They keep writing in the same genres.
So you look at the first climate,
the epistles of St. Ignatius as my co-host is want to do.
I am.
and...
And they're the same genre pretty much as the epistles you find in the New Testament.
Right.
I mean, if you read St. Ignatius, and a lot of scholars will say this.
I mean, it's not me.
It reads a lot like a kind of merger of Paul and John.
Like the tone is similar to the content.
The content is definitely Joe and I, but he seems to make reference to, say, Paul's works.
interesting actually that he doesn't ever quote John.
which, but his theology is very joe and I, and which kind of suggests that he just simply
got the theology from the Apostle directly and wasn't being mediated to him by a book.
But yeah, it reads like the New Testament.
St. Ignatius reads like his works could be part of the New Testament.
And you know, Cheppard of Hermes is a prophetic book.
A pistol of Barnabas looks a lot like Hebrews.
and
In fact, you find people arguing that Barnabas wrote Hebrews and their church fathers,
and their argument is, well, look how much it looks like the epistle of St. Barnabas.
So much the bit remains by St. Barnabas. You have stuff like the apocalypse, Peter, you have
gospels, you have, right? They're writing in the same genres, they just keep writing and
pursuing this literary activity, right? And so, and there's a big swath of this stuff that's
You can go on your phone and check it out.
I'll do it.
not heretical. Yeah, obviously, including the Apostolic fathers, obviously, including, you
know, the other early church fathers, but also including some of these other books, right?
Like the gospel of Nicodemus that Father Andrew read from back at Pascat, right? These Christian
texts of Aceopoli goes on into the Middle Ages, right? And so no one was reading these other
attacks and arguing they should be tacked onto the end of the New Testament.
Right, because again...
That's not how canon works.
Right. And none of them, even were bothered by the fact that they knew that St. Peter didn't write the apocalypse of St. Peter.
And they knew St. Nicodemus didn't write the gospel of Nicodemus.
Yeah.
They didn't react to it as, this is a lie. This is a threat that looked at the contents.
Right. And this is a fine contents.
And this is the way that some people have labeled this idea of apocrypha at
that it's deceptive in some way, you know, that it's attempting to to see to to pull a fast one, you know.
Right. So you have just as you've had in every era, right? You have texts that are canonical that
have this ritual life and life of authority and the public life of the community. And then you just
also have a lot of popular Christian texts, right? Christian texts that are edifying stories and
and traditions that are passed down, x.
of different apostles, the actual Saint Paul, the actual Saint Peter, right? There's tons
of tons and tons of these, which not unlike our own era in which there are books being written
that are not heretical. There are saints lives collected. There's all kinds of texts that,
you know, no one will ever say that any of my books should be part of the Bible. No one
will ever say that.
You know, you can't, you never know.
Okay, someone, some crazy...
easy nut might so yes, yes, but but they get your own L Ron Hubbard someday
Start out being a bad science fiction writer. Yeah
After nuclear World War III right in the ravages
Someone might find a copy of orthodoxy and heterodoxy
Found a whole new civilization on it God help him if it's just the last chapters like the comms and the Yangs
Anyway, so I had to get another Star Trek reference in.
So, yeah, and we see that this isn't just like sort of an early church phenomena, like,
oh, well, they hadn't sorted it all out yet.
Right, and eventually when this stuff gets sorted out, they sort of get rid of all that
other stuff, right?
Yeah.
That's not true.
Right.
And one of the big places we see that is
is in the work of George S. and Kellos and St. Nicholas
or the confessor of Constantinople.
George S. and Kellos did most of the writing on what's
called the chronography, which was sort of the history
of the world.
It was a universal history.
It's a history world up to that time.
And then he lived at the end of the eighth century,
the very end.
And sort of the history of the world up
to that.
time making use of all kinds of extrabiblical literature, including the book of
Enic and stuff. And sort of appended to the end of that by St.
Nicoporos of Constantinople, who was... So George and Kellos is called St.
Kellos because he was the Selmaid, monastic cell, of St.
Tarasios of Constantinople, who was the patriarch before St.
Nicoporos. So St. Nicoporos becomes patriarch after St.
Drosios, he publishes George St. Kellos's.
chronography, he appended to it a listing of texts. And on it he lists for the
Old Testament and the New Testament. So this is beginning of the 9th century,
St. Nicholas lists, here's the books that everybody acknowledges in the Old
Testament. Here's the books that some people acknowledge and not others. And here
Where are the Old Testament apocrypha?
The private books.
Then he lists, here are the New Testament books that everyone accepts.
Here are the New Testament books that some people use and not others.
And that's not just revelation, but it includes revelation.
Includes the apocalypse of Saint Peter, believe it or not.
And the gospel of the Hebrews.
And then he lists the New Testament apocrypha, which includes things like the epistles of
St. A. N. A. S. and the shepherd of Hermes and a bunch of first clement, these things.
a lot of climatine literature.
So that idea, right, that there are these two categories of books to be read, one in public in the churches, right,
which he defines descriptively, right? Here's the ones that all the churches are using. Here's the one that some are and some aren't, right.
He defines that category descriptively, and then he says, here are the other books that are, you know, to be used in the home.
and we find that it's those books that he lists as apocrypha.
those privately read books, those are the ones that we find preserved at
monastic settlements, right? So Jewish communities don't preserve like the
testament of the 12 patriarchs, or the story of Joseph and Asinath, right? They
don't preserve, even first Inek, these aren't preserved by Jewish groups,
because rabbinic Judaism repudiates all these books. These books are preserved
in Orthodox monasteries. Right. That's where we get the testament of the 12
Patrex's Mount Athos, Marsaba.
these major ancient monastery foundations.
They preserve the second temple Jewish texts
and these early Christian texts, right?
Which they do not think are part of the scriptures
that they are not reading publicly in church,
but that they think are important.
Yeah.
And should be read.
Yeah, right.
They're not just copying them as kind of weird antiquarians.
You know, look, here's this ancient text that we have.
Let's make sure that we have copies of it.
as someday scholars are going to want to look at this.
you know, it's for spiritual edification.
Right.
That's why they keep them around.
There are a lot more books that they didn't copy than that they did.
Yeah.
So the ones they did, they did because they thought they were really important.
Right.
Because it's not just, oh, here's a cool thing to put in my library.
You copy a book.
That's a lot of time and effort and expense.
Right.
And so it is, it's that understanding.
that understand.
of this middle category, this third category, the books to be privately read that are not read
publicly as scripture, that provides the paradigm for understanding the role of the writings of
the later Church fathers, right? So some of those are apostolic fathers, but the later Church
fathers, right? The people who we call the Church fathers and their writings, the role of their
authority in the life of the Church, right, is within that same kind of category, right?
Right.
Yes, we read St. John Crassostom's Pascale.
homily at Posca, right? But we aren't reading a description. Right? I'm reading that homily
instead of me trying to give one because I can't do better than he did. Yeah, it's not,
yeah, it's worth noting that not everything that is read out loud in church equals canonical
scripture. Right. I'm sorry and is not canonical scripture. Right. And you know, the, the,
the, the homily you're going to preach on Sunday is not the scripture. You know, right?
There is a liturgical ritual act that takes place in an orthodox...
before you read scripture.
Right.
Before I have it.
There's blessings that are given.
There's, right.
Right.
You know, we literally pray that we would be made
worthy to hear the gospel before it's read to us.
Right.
So yeah, so it is part of this liturgical ritual act.
Remember, that's what we're talking about with these texts.
Right.
It's not just authority in some banal sense.
It's not authority in the sense that the text itself
has this authority and commands us to do things
we must obey the text.
Right, right, but it serves this ritual function and that function is to
Give us access to the experience of God in Christ. Yeah
And we don't do that with even the Possible homily say Chuck or Sons worth a cynics are in or
Right or any other text, but we do read them
Right and get a lot out of them and they are they are preserved and so
So this is sort of what I think of every once in a while.
somebody will critique father Andrew and or I, right?
For talking about these extra canonical texts.
And they'll say why are you talking about
these extra canonical texts?
Either you shouldn't be talking about them at all
or more mildly, you know, hey,
there's a lot of folks out there
who haven't even read the Bible, right?
So why are you talking to them about
and potentially getting them to read these other things
that aren't in the Bible, right?
And what I think is, well...
you know, saying John Chrysostom isn't in the Bible, right?
Say Gregory the theologian isn't in the Bible.
Say Gregory Polymoss isn't in the Bible.
Say Max was a confessor isn't in the Bible.
Say an iron as if he don't isn't in the Bible.
I would certainly encourage people to read those, right?
Now, if you ask me, should you read the whole Bible first?
I'd probably say, yeah, that'd be good, right?
Because it'll help you understand what the fathers are saying,
because they read the Bible a lot, right?
But I wouldn't say like no, you are not allowed to...
read anything but the Bible until you have read the whole Bible. That doesn't make a lot
of sense to me. These other things are outside the Bible too, but they have this role. And
the reason they have that role is why? Well because in another way, in a derivative way,
they're providing the same function. They're helping connect us to the experience of God
in Jesus Christ. Right. But in a different way.
not can jubilee is only
make the most possible sense in light of Genesis
and they help us to understand Genesis.
Is a lot of what's really going on there.
And the interpretation of other parts of the Bible.
Yeah.
That calender.
The intersection really, as a nerd, it's interesting,
but doesn't really help you understand much of the Bible.
No, right.
And I think it's worth pointing out
that the way that the church bothers.
talk about these kinds of texts, the way that they cite them and the way that they treat
them is basically the way that we cite and treat the church fathers, meaning that the church
fathers, their writings function essentially in the same way that the earliest apocrypha
function. They're alongside, you know, they're part of the tradition, they're alongside the
but they are not the scriptures and they're not held in the same way or
in the same way or regarded as reliable in the same way.
At least they shouldn't be.
Right, right exactly.
You know, by the church they're not, I should say.
Maybe by individual people who kind of get off kilter,
but the church's tradition.
So this is part of the problem of what happens in the West.
When you take a binary view of authority and you apply it to the church fathers.
Yeah, either two or false.
picture or absolutely false. So on one side you get some of the extreme positions within Roman Catholicism.
There are yes there are a number of positions within Roman Catholicism, but there are some sort of
extreme positions in Roman Catholicism which hold that anybody who's considered a church father,
especially anybody who's been named a doctor of the church in the Roman Catholic church,
is essentially infallible. Right, you're not at least not allowed to just go and say yeah,
Yeah, this guy was wrong.
Say to Gus was just wrong about that.
Right.
If there are contradictions, you have to try to reconcile them.
If it seems like St. Augustine is saying something wrong,
like see how Thomas Aquinas reads St. Augustine.
Well, it seems like St. Augustine is saying this,
but he can't really be saying that because that's wrong.
So he must actually be saying this other thing.
Right?
So that's one extreme.
And then the other extreme would be, and again,
there are a variety of positions within Protestantism.
but the other extreme would be some of this
really extreme forms of solar scriptura where it's like anything that's not in the Bible, right?
If it's not in the Bible, it's a pack of lies, right? So don't come to me with your church fathers.
Don't come at me with your, you know, don't come into me and tell me that St. Peter was crucified in Rome because that ain't in the Bible
So that's not true. It's false because it's not the Bible, right?
That way again, that that's not all Protestants. That's an extreme, right? Yeah, so I'm putting out the two extremes in the West, right?
but both of those extremes were...
from that kind of binary view of authority.
Yeah, right. Where it's not like a continuum, right?
Right. But what we see is that there is this middle category,
you know, not considered infallible, but shouldn't be just regarded either.
Right. Yeah. Right.
And so what this all ultimately comes down to is the orthodox understanding of
of Holy Tradition.
Right that that tradition is not the transmission of data right?
This is the way sometimes you hear tradition talked about is oral tradition right which is
Yeah, there's this stuff that we didn't write down that the bishops just told each other when they got consecrated
Like passed down to today the secret and Jake nobody ever wrote it down any place, right?
That's not what we're talking about
Right, that's not what we're talking about when in the Orthodox Church
which we talk about holy tradition, we're talking about the life of the holy
spirit in the church, which is an ongoing thing. Right? So it's not a problem for us that
we don't know who wrote a book of the Old Testament or we don't know exactly when it was written,
or it was compiled and edited over centuries. That's not a problem for us because we believe the
Holy Spirit was involved in that whole process. Right? Right from beginning to end. And in the
transmission of that final text quote unquote, right, what is done down to us today, the Holy Spirit
it was involved in that.
to. Hoysperic has evolved to the whole thing, right? And so we don't have to argue about
a specific act, right? A specific point in time, right? And so what we look at, the place
where we see the life of the Hoysperic unfolding in the church, is essentially in reception
history, right? In the way in which things were received, because things aren't always
clear at the time that they're happening. Right, you're kind of, you know, there's the...
the fog of war in some sense, you know, with heretical controversies with all kinds of stuff like that.
The scriptures tell us this, the Holy Spirit blows where he will, right? So we don't always know
at the time, right? But we can see after the fact, right? We can see after the fact.
Yeah, there's a sort of digesting that happens. And so this is the core of why it's not important
who wrote the books of the Bible when they were written.
How early or how
it was, what language it was written in. None of that really matters because what holds
authority in my church community is what holds authority in my church community, which
is a particular form of those certain texts that we have today. Doesn't matter when
that form came to be? Does it matter how? Does it matter who? Right? It's descriptive.
This is just the case.
Yeah.
And it should be noted that it's also not to say that all authority for these things
resides in the group of people who happen to be gathering to get to, like, you could
not, you know, even your bishop could not get together with the rest of his son and say,
okay, we're going to take a vote and replace the canon.
Right.
That's just not how, so it's not a matter of, you know, authoritative offices either.
they physically could.
Right, right, but here's what would happen over the next century we'd find out if they were right or not. Yeah
Right as the other was rejected by the rest of the church. Yeah, exactly and they were no longer bishops
Cast out of the church. We would say oh Holy Spirit found it gets that one, right? Yeah, right, right
So it's not it's not just a matter of saying here's the office that's allowed to make these determinations
Right, there is no office that make there are no determinations made
made.
Right?
Yeah.
Maybe by the Holy Spirit.
If you want to try and figure out how the mind of God works, good luck.
You don't even know what it's like to be a bat.
Right?
You know, you can't translate hours into Jeremy Baramese.
You don't know how this all works.
Nice.
That's a nice reference.
Yeah.
And then this also, you know, this also transmits to how we understand church councils.
Right?
Like, there are some people-
Which is how we understand everything.
Yeah, right.
Exactly.
Exactly. Yeah, no, not only church councils, but, but like, you know, for instance, there are people that wants to
tinker or critique or whatever particular church councils because they have an interest in
overturning their decisions or editing them or this kind of thing saying, well, you know,
this council, that's not what really went down there because it was changed later on.
And you know, a kind of fraud was perpetuated on the church.
you
later on and it's like, well, that's again, that's not how this works. Let's look at how the church
has received that council has confirmed it has repeated it has sung it. You either believe that
the Holy Spirit works in that process or you don't and if you don't believe that the Holy Spirit
actually worked in that process of reception, then what are we doing here? You know, like what
that it's irrelevant.
Yeah.
Then who cares what a bunch of bishops decided?
Right.
a thousand years ago. Right. If the Holy Spirit wasn't involved, I don't care. Right. You can't say
that they pulled a fast one or even some emperor pulled a fast one. Right. And the church has been
getting this wrong for centuries upon centuries. No, that is not a thing within the Orthodox church.
Yeah. Yeah. Right. Because the Orthodox church would have to cease to exist. Right. Right. Because
because you'd have to say that the Holy Spirit is not.
live guiding guiding the life of the church.
And we see this with ecumenical councils, right?
Yeah, council of Florence looked like an ecumenical council
ever signed off on it.
Bishop's there signed off on it.
Wasn't an ecumenical council.
Yeah, I mean, I don't know if you noticed,
but we're not in communion with the Roman Catholic Church.
I have noticed this.
Yeah, I mean, one, you know, one bishop is the holdout,
But at the time, it looks like...
Okay, we've got this one dissident, but I mean all of the rest of these wise and holy men are all saying yes
You know now we look back and then say thank you mark of emphasis for holding out, you know
Yeah, right and that happens all the time and so I'll just go ahead and address the elephant in the room
Sorry, orginess and universalist at all
It doesn't matter what you construct is having it really happened at the Fifth Medical Council
Yep.
It was received as a condemnation of particular elements.
of origins, theology, and of universalism.
So it doesn't matter.
You can do all the history work in the world.
No reconstruction.
You can try and reconstruct the quote-unquote original text of a biblical book.
You can do that all day.
It can be fun.
But your reconstruction at the end of the day has no authority in the church.
Because that's not how it works.
Yeah.
It just doesn't.
construction has nothing to do with the Holy Spirit.
I mean, we kind of alluded it to this earlier,
like what do you do if you're living in the midst
of some kind of church controversy?
As seems to always be the case
throughout the whole history of the church,
there's always something going on.
It's be as faithful as you can in the midst of it,
and you kind of have to muddle through on some level, right?
Like, it's just how it is.
I mean, what else can you do?
If you're looking for utter certainty,
We don't get that in this life.
You know, it's just not, well, uncertainty of what?
Right.
You know, which party to pick, which thing to sign off on?
You know?
Yeah.
Yes.
My salvation does not hinge in any way on anything ecclesiastical or geopolitical going on in Ukraine
right now.
Right.
You don't have to take a side in part of the meeting.
You're living in Ukraine at my.
Right.
So I'm not, you know, belittling that.
but for the...
out that people say in the United States are all worked up about that, all those related
issues, right? You don't need any certainty about that in terms of your salvation, right?
We all know what we're supposed to be doing for our salvation.
And we, you know, also thinking about church councils, we can't look back at them and say,
ah, here are the marks of ecumenicity because for any collection of those marks of ecumenicity
you're going to find some counsel that qualifies and yet isn't received as
ecumenical or you're going to find a counsel that doesn't quite qualify and yet
is received as ecumenical because that's just the way that the church sort of
received it. That's that's the way that it goes. If this whole post-doc thing it's
not just councils, right? You'll get this with when people start talking about
the canon. They're like, well here are the criteria for canonical books. It
was a bit of an apostle then you're like what about the Old Testament?
Yeah, yeah, it was written in this period.
Like, and again, that...
presupposes that there was like some committee that's a town it came up you know right here's the
criteria we will use that's all post-hoc that's all looking back on it and saying right well these
are the things I've received as canonical yeah I don't want to just say I receive these by tradition
for whatever reason right that I've received these handed down to me and so I'm going to try and
make some argument after yeah some sort of formal criteria that makes tradition what it is yeah
Yeah, right.
X-turnles.
Yeah.
You know, yeah.
I mean, if that's how you get your kicks, go ahead, but it's kind of a waste of time.
I waste a lot of time.
So I'm going to say this is a nice story.
I mean, the same is true of liturgical practice, right?
Because liturgical change, liturgical change is a thing.
There's even liturgical reform.
You know, now in the history of the Orthodox Church, we're never talking about a liturgical
reform on the level of, of say, for instance, what happens after the Second Vatican Council
Roman Catholic Church but there are electrical reforms.
There's of course the Niconian reforms in the 17th century in Russia, which were hugely problematic at the time for sure
But largely are what is received as modern Russian Orthodox liturgical practice
And the but also you know in the Greek speaking world there was Saint Philotheos Kokinos
He was a liturgical reformer and kind of streamliner. He's the guy who can and I stink Gregory Palomas
and
And I should mention, since I'm God willing going there and not
too long, he's the guy who canonized the three Holy Martyrs of Vilnius.
So here, there you go.
You know, the surgical reform is a thing.
How do we know that it was good?
A particular reform is good, a particular change,
or introduction to something is good,
by seeing how it's received.
What, you know?
Seeing how history, reality, play down.
Yeah, I mean, in the moment, it may not be clear.
You may not know how to evaluate it.
You know, but it's okay.
Yeah.
to take sides of these things.
salvation. And this is true in terms of church fathers, right? Who's a father and who's not? Who's a
saint and who's not? How prominent is a given church father and his works compared to another
church father and his works? Or mother of the church and her? All right. Which works were
preserved and which ones weren't? Yeah. Right? Church fathers wrote a lot of stuff that didn't get
handed down to us and some stuff that did. What works by people who are...
saints, people like origin, and tertolian, etc., right, did get handed down to us
and why, and in what context, right? All of those things are guided by the Holy Spirit, right?
And so we take our cues from that, right? Descriptive, not prescriptive. Right. Yeah, which means that
reconstructions or attempts to correct the record are not the way that Orthodox Christianity works.
trying to correct reality. Good luck with that. Right. Yeah. So, you know, one might
therefore ask then since a lot of what we, a big piece of what we try to do on this podcast
is to direct people's attention to things that often it's not being directed to. Are we
trying to revise the church? Right? Are we trying to? I know, I know. But, you know, it's good
to ask these questions.
Is that what we're trying to do?
Is we're trying to...
say, oh, let's dig up this stuff that no one's talking about and bring it back out in the
open. And, you know, and, and, you know, even though the church hasn't received this, we're
going to make everybody receive it now. Like, is that what we're actually trying to do?
No. I don't, I don't know. I don't have the timber in my voice to do that, the way that you do.
Yeah. So, yeah, the issue is, right? If we were doing this show in Greek and Greece or in
Russian
in Russia, right?
We sort of wouldn't be doing this show.
We'd be doing a different show, right?
Because it would be a wholly different context.
So the reality is that you and I are both in the United
States, right?
But even if we broaden that to sort of Anglophone
orthodoxy, right, to include some former British imperial
holdings, Anglophone orthodoxy isn't
just
in its childhood or infancy, it's like a fetus, right?
It's still like being born.
Some kind of real sense of anglophone orthodoxy.
And it's kind of a mess.
We have random bits and bobs of all kinds of things
in English.
A lot of them aren't even translated by orthodox people.
And in some cases that affects the translations.
I'm not just talking about church.
I'm talking about liturgical stuff.
I'm talking about liturgical lives.
I mean, some of the earliest orthodox and
surgical translations in English were done by Isabel
Hapgood, who was an Episcopalian?
Yeah.
I mean, you have to pull together two or three different projects
even to get a complete new translation of the whole Bible
made by Orthodox Christians in English.
This stuff just doesn't exist, right, in English.
And so I see what we're doing here as us going and finding all this stuff in the tradition,
right, some of it not in English, right, and trying to bring it to the attention of Orthodox
Christians here in the US who don't have access to it.
Yeah.
It's sort of a translation project on some level, right, like monks on Mount Athos for centuries
have if they wanted it had access.
potentially to the testament of the 12 patriarchs. Most American Orthodox
Christians don't know what I'm talking about. Right. So is that me trying to
change the American Orthodox? Well, I don't think so. I think it's me saying, hey,
here's something or the dogs you don't know about, right? Try to get some more
of this and I'm only qualified to do a certain little piece of it. Right, right.
I can't do nothing with music, man.
I can't carry a tune in a bucket.
I can't help you with liturgical music.
I can't help anybody with that.
And I'm not an expert on everything.
I'm an expert on a tiny little sliver of things.
And I kind of know some stuff about the broader things related
to the scriptures.
But so I could try and help fill in some of that stuff.
But we actually need a whole lot of other people doing this,
But doing it with other areas, right?
with liturgical music, with church fathers of different eras, with cannons in the sense of the
structures of the church, with church history, right? We need all of this and we need it for years
and years and years so that we can maybe in a few centuries have an American Orthodox church.
That's a real and vital Orthodox church, not that America will be here by then.
But in English speaking Orthodox church somewhere in whatever's left.
Wow, now that you've pronounced our doom, we're in mid-collapse.
man. You were. Yeah, I know. I know. That's true. All right, well, just some some final thoughts
now here for our episode on textual authority. You know, along the way we critiqued a number
of ways of looking at texts, right? For instance, the desire to find, you know, like we,
in our, especially in our episode about how to read the Bible, you know, this desire to find
with
sort of behind the text or what was in the mind of the author, this kind of thing.
We didn't talk about that as much tonight but that's related also to this question
of attempting to reconstruct a basis for why certain books of the Bible are canonical.
Reconstruct a basis for how ecumenical councils are ecumenical, you know, who's a church
I mean, the list goes on and on and on, right?
And...
What I believe, and now I certainly believe that a lot of these attempts are well intended,
right?
But there is nonetheless, even if they're well intended, if the person has their mind
to do something good, there is still a very problematic spiritual motion going on with
that, right?
And it's that a desire to get a handle on something that you can't...
get a handle on. I understand wanting to get a handle on stuff. I mean, I'm an inherently
curious person. I want to understand things. I want to take complex systems and try to figure
out how to, you know, to talk about them to people. I get it, right? I get it. And I think
it's important to try to get a handle on trying to understand, right? What's going on in
Orthodox tradition. But when we attempt to create a kind of system
that is the basis for how authority is assigned.
Then that's a kind of trying to get a handle on things
that is actually stepping away from the way
that the Orthodox tradition actually works.
And the beginning of really understanding how it works
is number one, accepting what it is as it is.
As it is, even if you don't agree with it
don't like it or are uncomprom-
with it or even offended by it, right? We receive the whole tradition. And then the task then is to try to
understand the tradition, right? Not to come up with a system for figuring out how it gains its
authority and all this kind of stuff. There's not, there is no system, there's no criteria, there's
There's no, you know, it just doesn't work that way, right?
So that's why I say there's
a different spiritual motion involved. The spiritual motion of attempting to create a system
for all of it is ultimately about trying to assert some kind of control over it. And I
think that's why so many people who attempt to do this end up in a lot of arguments and
debates over it, which is not how the tradition actually works.
Certainly you have...
debate and argument within the Orthodox tradition. But largely it has a pastoral purpose of rescuing people
from being drawn away from Christ. It's not just about being right about certain things.
And it's done by the people who have been given the task to shepherd people and to care for them.
You know, we mentioned, for instance, the feast of the Ecumenical Council, the Feasts of the Fathers.
And we've talked about this on the show before, you know, and there's that reading,
and the old testament reading from Genesis that's given investors about how Abram, along
with his 318 guys, goes and rescues his nephew Lot, and it's not coincidence that the traditional
number of fathers at the First Ackermere Council was 318, whether that was literally the
actual head count there is not the point.
The point is that they were engaged in a rescue mission for the church.
They were...
rescuing them people from error.
Right? Because that's their task.
That's their job as the shepherds of the church.
They weren't trying to create a system of authority to impose so
that they would be obeyed.
They were reaching out in love to bring people back towards Christ.
Right?
And that's the spiritual motion that we need to...
engage in. It's the spiritual motion of accepting the tradition. I mean, you
notice that the ecumenical councils, they begin with following the Holy
Father's, right? Not we have come up with a system. But following the, we're
followers, you know, of the fathers, or fathers of the apostles, we've received
the tradition and now we're reiterating it in an appropriate way at this time and
place to deal with whatever is in front of us. You know, it's, it's ultimately,
it ultimately comes down to pro
and humility. It comes down to pride and humility. And you can see when I know when I'm filled
with pride, I want to show everybody how right I am and to defeat them. You know, when someone
has humility, then it works in a very, very different way. And then actually the beautiful
thing is that when you approach the orthodox tradition with humility, then it opens up
in front of you as this beautiful, beautiful tap.
of endless possibility of exploration and and diving deeper into its depths. I know I'm kind of mixing my metaphors
but you get what I mean I think. And so I mean that's my encouragement is to to enter into it with with a sense of wonder
you know and wonder is based on humility. And that's that's how we receive the orthodox tradition and
and that's how we're able to see and to describe how it is that texts.
function authoritatively within the church's tradition. So Father Stephen, what are your final comments?
So I think maybe some folks have gotten a wrong impression in terms of what we're about,
not through any fault of their own. So we write from the beginning, like from the beginning of each
episode and from
beginning of doing this podcast have been highly critical of materialism meaning you know scientific
materialism the idea that the material is all that exists right the material is the real and
that's the limit of it. And the reason I think some folks may have gotten a misinterpretation is
recently when I've taken to as has been my want for some time to bash in Plato I think people have
gotten confused, right?
Because...
I think the easiest place for people to try to take refuge when they reject materialism
is to try to go to the other end and become idealists, right?
And try and deal with things in the realm of ideas as if that's spiritual reality, right?
And so what I think we're actually doing is neither materialism.
nor idealism but realism right dealing with reality. I think you see that in our approach like tonight
Right, we're dealing with well, how did these
texts actually become canonical in history? How did it really happen in the real world?
Right as opposed to the kind of idealist approach which would be
what does Canonicity mean? What are the marks? What is my
theological system in terms of how the scriptures work and then therefore what does that require the scriptures to be?
And then what do I need to say about canonicity based on that to fit with the rest of these ideas?
It's very easy and maybe even comforting is an escape because reality is not so great.
right to go into that
of ideas and act like, hey, if we could just get these ideas hammered out, if we could just get
people have the right ideas and the right understandings and people's heads, if we could just get people
to look at these things in the right way and hold the right opinions, that will cause a change,
in the world and reality, and the material will sort of fix itself. And the problem is that
That doesn't work.
What you end up producing...
is a fantasy. It's very easy for theology, even good theology, even technically correct theology
to just become fantasy. It's really easy for it to become the same thing as, you know, Star Trek
Canon is in my head, right? Or Marvel or DC comic book Canon is in my head. Theology can come to be
essentially the same thing. It's very easy in theological debates with theology to become something
something like that.
Right, I use the right words, the right technical terms.
I put them in the right order and use the right conjunctions.
Therefore, I am orthodox and I have correct theology.
And usur are not orthodox.
Therefore, you have bad theology.
And I'm going to argue that my conjunctions are correct and
yours are wrong.
And then if I feel like or if people tell me I won the argument,
then I will have won a great victory for orthodoxy.
And maybe that'll help myself, Asian or something.
Um, um,
But none of that is connected to reality in any way.
St. James told us a long time ago, true religion is care for widows and orphans and keeping yourself pure from the world.
Religion is about what you do, not because the material is all that there is, but because the spiritual things that we talk about on this show,
Whether it's angels and demons, whether it's the Holy Spirit,
LOOP!
through the church, directing the church, these are not ideas. These are things
that are real. They're real in addition to the material being real, right? We're
talking about more reality that includes but is not limited to the material.
That's where we find our salvation is Orthodox Christians in our material
bodies in this world, in communities with other people who often smell bad,
that.
and don't look pretty to us all the time.
And don't dress the way we think they should.
And don't say things to us that we always like.
And don't go along with our great ideas.
And disagree with us about our brilliant ideas.
That's the reader where all of salvation has worked out.
Right? And so we start with rather than ideas
and A.
theology that exists in the realm of imagination, we start with an understanding of God that's based in reality.
The reality of the churches that exist, the reality of what the Holy Spirit has done through history, the reality of the lives lived by the saints before us.
All of that reality is our basis, and then we take that reality and we apply it in reality,
to caring for others, to helping others, to loving others.
And it's when we
do that that our salvation is further that things fall into place, right? You will never
have assurance of your salvation or standing before God based on ideas because you can't
trick yourself that well. You can't get out of having doubts about things through ideas.
You can't deceive yourself that well. The only way to get past doubts and the only way to
get past fears.
The only way to have any kind of assurance of your relationship with Christ is to actually
experience it in reality and the way you do that is concretely by loving others, by participating
in worship, by being part of a community, by loving people and being loved, right?
And by participating.
That's where you're going to find salvation, that's where Christ is going to become real
to you.
And all of the ideas in the world are ultimately irrelevant in the face of...
what we actually live and do and practice and experience and become.
So those are my final thoughts for this evening.
Amen.
Well, that is our show for today.
Thank you very much for listening everyone.
If you didn't get through to us live, as we were monitoring our social media
channels tonight, we'd still love to hear from you.
You can email us at Lordofspiritsatheachandfate.com.
You can message us at our Facebook page or you can leave us a voicemail.
at SpeakPipe.com slash Lord of Spirits.
And in a general sense, you should join us for our live broadcast on the second and
fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern, 4 p.m. Pacific, but the one in two weeks is pre-recorded.
So it's like, that was the next.
And if you are on Facebook, you can like our page and join our discussion group.
You can leave ratings and reviews everywhere, but most importantly,
please share this show with a friend. Tell someone about it.
And finally be sure to go to www.engshafate.com.stroke.com
and help make...
sure we and lots of other AFR podcasters stay on the air and come back in a month when
we'll have a very special guest.
Thank you, good night and God bless you.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung, a listener-supported presentation of Ancient
Faith Radio.
and I'd be held and I-
I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne, and the beasts, and the elders,
and the number of them was ten thousand times ten thousand, and thousands of thousands,
seeing with a loud voice worthy as the land that was slain to receive power, and riches,
and wisdom, and strength, and honor, and glory, and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.